<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A thankefull remembrance of Gods mercy to several persons at Quabaug or Brookfield partly in a collection of providences about them, and gracious appearances for them: and partly in a sermon preached by Mr. Edward Bulkley, Pastor of the Church of Christ at Concord, upon a day of thanksgiving, kept by divers for their wonderfull deliverance there. Published by Capt. Thomas VVheeler. [Five lines from Psalms]</title>
            <author>Wheeler, Thomas, ca. 1620-1676.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 134 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96298</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1600</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC W35426</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99897885</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99897885</idno>
            <idno type="VID">136195</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96298)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 136195)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2537:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A thankefull remembrance of Gods mercy to several persons at Quabaug or Brookfield partly in a collection of providences about them, and gracious appearances for them: and partly in a sermon preached by Mr. Edward Bulkley, Pastor of the Church of Christ at Concord, upon a day of thanksgiving, kept by divers for their wonderfull deliverance there. Published by Capt. Thomas VVheeler. [Five lines from Psalms]</title>
                  <author>Wheeler, Thomas, ca. 1620-1676.</author>
                  <author>Bulkley, Edward, d. 1696.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 10 [i.e. 14], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed and sold by Samuel Green,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Cambridge [Mass.] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errors in paging: p. 14, 2nd count, and p. 18, 3rd count, misnumbered 10, 17.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the John Carter Brown Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hutchinson, Edward, 1613-1675 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>King Philip's War, 1675-1676 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Brookfield (Mass.) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:136195:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:136195:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A Thankefull REMEMBRANCE OF GODS MERCY To ſeveral Perſons at Quabaug or BROOKFIELD:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Partly in a Collection of Providences about them, and Gracious Appearances for them: And partly in a Sermon Preached By <hi>Mr. EDWARD B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LKLEY,</hi> Paſtor of the Church of Chriſt at <hi>Concord,</hi> upon a day of Thanksgiving, kept by divers for their Wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Deliverance there.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by Capt. <hi>THOMAS VVHEELER.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 107.8.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Oh that men would Praiſe the Lord for his Goodneſs, and his Wonderfull Works to the Children of men.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 111.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The Works of the LORD are great, ſought out of all thoſe that Love him.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>CAMBRIDGE,</hi> Printed and Sold by <hi>Samuel Green</hi> 1676.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:136195:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:136195:2"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> 
               <hi>Purpoſing to Publiſh this enſuing Narrative of Gods Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence towards</hi> Capt. Hutchinſon <hi>&amp;</hi> my felfe <hi>&amp;</hi> others, &amp; the <hi>Sermon</hi> preached on the occaſion hereafter expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: do Judge it expdient to give you a little further Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of matrers, occaſioning the going of <hi>Captain Hutchinſon</hi> &amp; my <hi>felſ</hi> to <hi>Quabaug:</hi> and alſo of the <hi>Motives</hi> inducing me to the Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of both to the world:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philip</hi> the Sachem of the <hi>Wampanôgs,</hi> lying about <hi>Mount-hope,</hi> having done ſome Acts of <hi>Hoſtility</hi> againſt <hi>Plimouth Colony</hi> by murdering men, burning Houſes and killing Cattel: the ſaid <hi>Colony</hi> was neceſſitated to wart with him in their own defence: The <hi>Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſachuſets</hi> and <hi>Connecticot Colonies</hi> being Confederate with them, and diſcerning the Juſtneſs of the Warr on their part: divers were ſent forth of each <hi>Colony</hi> both Troopers and foot Souldiers to help our Brethren of that <hi>Colony</hi> againſt the ſaid <hi>Sachem.</hi> The <hi>Honoured Council</hi> of the <hi>Maſſachuſets</hi> did alſo ſend <hi>Captain Hutchinſon</hi> with a Guard to the <hi>Narroganſet Suchems</hi> and <hi>Sagamores;</hi> who were not farr from the ſaid <hi>Philip:</hi> to ſee whether they intended to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue their peace with us, or to joyne with the <hi>Wampanôgs</hi> againſt us: They promiſed to continue their peace with us, which they gave further hopes that they would do by ſending over more of their <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chems</hi> to our <hi>Council</hi> where they alſo promiſed to remain Faithful Friends to us. Our much Honoured <hi>Governour</hi> and <hi>Council,</hi> being deſirous as farr as it might be to prevent ſhedding of blood, and the ſtrengthening of the Enemy by others joyning with them, did alſo ſend <hi>Ephraim Curtis</hi> of <hi>Sudbury</hi> and others to ſeveral other
<pb facs="tcp:136195:3"/>
               <hi>Sachems</hi> in and about the <hi>Nipmuck</hi> Country to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, they alſo promiſed Faithful Friendſhip to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> (though they afterwards proved wretchedly perfidious) and ſet a time wherein they would come to <hi>Boston</hi> further to engage them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for the Councils ſatisfaction, but they came not at the time appointed: The <hi>Council</hi> ſent the ſaid <hi>Ephraim Curtis</hi> again to know the Reaſon thereof. They again promiſed to come, but did not. The <hi>Honoured Council</hi> being willing to uſe all means to prevent a Wart with them if it might be, and their Aſſiſtance of <hi>Philip,</hi> and the reſt then in Arms againſt us: ſent <hi>Captain Hutchinſon</hi> thither alſo to Treat with them in order to the Preſervation of peace between us and them, they alſo appointed my ſelf to Aſſiſt him with part of my <hi>Troop,</hi> which accordingly I did attend: We diſcerned by the <hi>Indians</hi> deſerting the places of their Abode that they were afraid of us: and therefore the better to effect our buſineſs in a peaceable way, and prevent <hi>Hostility</hi> on either ſide before we marched all to them, we ſent three <hi>Engliſh men,</hi> and oue <hi>Indian</hi> (all four, being men Familiarly acquainted with many of the <hi>Indians</hi>) to let them underſtand that we only deſired a Treaty in Reference to the Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Peace with them, and that we inrcnded no hurt at all to them: but the Iſſue thereof was as in the <hi>Narrative</hi> is expreſſed. <hi>Wherein the Providences of God towards us in his wares about us were ſo Remarkable, in our ſore Exerciſes and gracious Deliverances that they ought never to be forgotten by us, but kept in Remembrance all our dayes: the Lord</hi> hath made his wonderful works to be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, <hi>ſaith the</hi> Pſalmiſt, <hi>and he would have his</hi> People to tell them to their Children, that they might alſo declare them to their Children, And therefore for the help of our memories and the preventing of miſtakes in Reports, and the <hi>Advantage of our own Relations and others better Acquaintance with the manner of Gods dealings with us,</hi> I have endeavoured the drawing up of this <hi>Following Declaration</hi> of what befell us in our <hi>March</hi> to, and at <hi>Brookfield,</hi> and our Returne homewards: I not at firſt intending that it ſhould by my means be brought to <hi>publick view:</hi> but ſeveral perſons having ſeen it, (though not altogether ſo large as now it is) they perſwaded me, and urged it as a <hi>Duty Incumbent</hi> on me, (the Lord having taken away <hi>Captain Hutchinſon,</hi> who might have performed it in a better
<pb facs="tcp:136195:3"/>manner) to put it forth in print, that many may thereby be provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>to give God the glory of his great works in our Salvation, and that others may make uſe of his dealings with us to learn to trust and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon him in the ſorest ſtraits, and may be encouraged to wait pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently for Deliverance in the greateſt danger that may befall them: for greater danger of</hi> Loſs of Life <hi>cannot well be with an</hi> Eſcape, <hi>then that of ours.</hi> For from <hi>Monday</hi> about <hi>Ten of the Clock</hi> in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning till <hi>nine on Wedneſday night, all hope that we ſhould be ſaved</hi> (as <hi>Acts</hi> 27.20) was in the Eye of Reaſon taken away, and we were in continual Expectation of Death, but yet even then we were not without ſome hopes <hi>in the Lord our God to whom the Iſſues of Death-belong:</hi> who was pleaſed <hi>to know our Souls in Adverſity, to hear our Cries, and to ſave us for his mercy ſake,</hi> as in the <hi>Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> more fully appears, which goodneſs of God that it may be the better remembred by us, and others incited the more <hi>to magnify God with us,</hi> (as <hi>David calls upon others to do for Gods mercy to him,</hi> Pſal 34.3.) <hi>and alſo quickned to put their trust on God all their dayes:</hi> I have Adventured to publiſh this <hi>Narration,</hi> intreating your <hi>Candid Acceptance</hi> thereof, and over looking all the defects and weakneſſes therein: As for the <hi>Sermon</hi> added thereto, the occaſion thereof was this. <hi>When the Lord of his free and abundant mercy had ſent</hi> Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance <hi>to us by</hi> Honoured Majors Willards <hi>coming to us, and our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies departing thereupon, and we had reſt from them, I in the morning called together my Company both the wounded and the Rest who were weary with their hard Service, and much watching, and propounded this to them; whether though God had taken away divers from us,</hi> &amp; <hi>others of us were ſore wounded, yet in regard ſo many of us had our Lives</hi> given us for a Prey, <hi>&amp; alſo that God had made us Inſtrumental to ſave ſo many Souls alive of the</hi> Town dwellers, <hi>(who would probably have been all or moſt of them deſtroyed, had not God carried us thither:) whether I ſay God did not Call for a</hi> Solemn day of Thanksgiving <hi>from us, when we ſhould have Opportunity: They Rejoycing at the motion very readily Aſſented to it, and promiſed that thoſe of us whom God ſhould be pleaſed to Carry home would attend it in due Seaſon: and when ſome others</hi> with my ſelf and Son, <hi>were in ſome good meaſure recovered of our wounds: I Requeſted</hi> Mr. <hi>Bulkely to help us in the work of the day intended to be kept by us. He being of a ready Spirit to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
<pb facs="tcp:136195:4"/>of his strength to forward any good duty that God calls for, he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Judging it to be of very great Concernment, althoughte he Country was in very great diſtreſs, our</hi> Deliverance <hi>being ſo</hi> Remarkable, he did joyne with us therein on <hi>October</hi> 21.75. and then preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed what is here publiſhed, which we finding ſo ſeaſonable to the <hi>occaſion and beneficial to our ſelves.</hi> I further Requeſted him that for the help of our memories, and our better Improvement of what was then delivered to us, alſo for the <hi>benefit</hi> and <hi>Edification</hi> of others, he would give me a <hi>Coppy</hi> of it, and ſuffer me to <hi>publiſh it:</hi> which though for a time he delayed to do, yet hath at length given given me a <hi>Coppy</hi> with power to do as I ſhall think beſt, therein per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting it to be added to the aforeſaid <hi>Narrative.</hi> I hope it may be profitable to many of Gods people, to whoſe view it may come, &amp; I know that there be many in this <hi>Country at this day</hi> for whome it may be very <hi>ſeaſonable,</hi> who having with our ſelves received <hi>great mercies in Preſervations and Deliverances in theſe Evil and Trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Times, in the</hi> Naraganſit Expedition, <hi>and at other times, and in other places where they have been in very great danger, and in</hi> hazard <hi>of the loſs of Life, and all they had, as alſo having been</hi> healed <hi>of</hi> ſore <hi>and</hi> dangerous wounds: <hi>been brought home ſafely to their</hi> dear Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, <hi>or have had their</hi> Relations Returned <hi>to them, whom they fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed they ſhould not have ſeen again, and have had their</hi> Habitations <hi>and</hi> Eſtates preſerved <hi>when near to Ruine; and others not farr from them were conſumed: All whom, with all others whom God hath vouchſaved any</hi> ſpecial mercy <hi>to in</hi> Recovery out of great ſickneſſes, <hi>or otherwiſe, it Concerns to do as we were then</hi> Exhorted <hi>to do, even</hi> ſeriouſly to obſerve what God hath done <hi>about them, and for them and Carefully to</hi> Return that Praiſe, Love and Obedience <hi>which he expects from them: I Crave your Prayers for the bleſſing of God to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company both his Works and his Word tous for our Everlaſting good.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho. Wheeler.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="narrative">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:136195:4"/>
            <head>A TR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E NARRATIVE</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Of the Lords Providences in various diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations towards Captain Edward Hutchinſon of Boston and my ſelf, and thoſe that went with us into the Nipmuck Country, and alſo to Quabaug, alias Brookfield: The ſaid Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Hutchinſon having a Commiſſion from the Honoured Council of this Colony to Treat with ſeveral Sachems in thoſe parts in order to the publick peace, and my ſelf being alſo ordered by the ſaid Council to accompany him with part of my Troop for Security from any dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that might be from the Indians: and to Aſſiſt him in the Tranſaction of matters com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to him.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſaid <hi>Captain Hutchinſon, and my ſelf</hi> with about twenty men or more marched from <hi>Cambridge</hi> to <hi>Sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury, July</hi> 28.75. and from thence into the <hi>Nipmuck Country,</hi> and finding that the <hi>Indians</hi> had deſerted their Towns, and we having gone until we came within <hi>twenty miles</hi> of <hi>New Norwitch,</hi> on <hi>July</hi> 31. (only we ſaw two <hi>Indians</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:136195:5"/>an Horſe with them, whom we would have ſpoke with, but they fled from us and left their Horſe, which we took) we then thought it not expedient to march any further that way, but ſet our march for <hi>Brookfield,</hi> whither we came on the Lords day about Noon. From thence the ſame day (being <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1.) we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that the <hi>Indians</hi> were about <hi>Ten Miles Northweſt</hi> from us, we ſent out <hi>four men</hi> to acquaint the <hi>Indians</hi> that we were not come to harm them, but our buſineſs was only to <hi>deliver a Meſſage</hi> from our Honoured <hi>Governour and Council</hi> to them, and to receive their <hi>Anſwer,</hi> we deſiring to come to a Treaty of Peace with them, (though they had for ſeveral dayes fled from us) they having before profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Friendſhip,</hi> and promiſed <hi>Fidelity</hi> to the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> When the Meſſengers came to them; they made an <hi>Alarm,</hi> and gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether about an <hi>hundred and Fifty</hi> fighting men as near as they could judge; The young men amongſt them were <hi>ſtout</hi> in their <hi>Speeches,</hi> and <hi>ſurly</hi> in their <hi>Carriage;</hi> But at length three of the <hi>chief Sachems</hi> promiſed to meet us on the next morning about <hi>eight of the Clock</hi> upon a plain within three miles of <hi>Brookfield,</hi> with which Anſwer the Meſſengers returned to us. Whereupon though their Speeches and Carriage did much diſcourage divers of our Company, yet we conceived that we had a cleer Call to go to meet them at the place whither they had promiſed to come. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly we with our men accompanied with <hi>three of the Principal Inhabitants</hi> of that Town marched to the plain appointed; but the <hi>Treacherous Heathen</hi> intending miſchief (if they could have op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity) came not to the ſaid place, and ſo failed our hopes of ſpeaking with them there. Whereupon the ſaid <hi>Captain Hutchin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and my ſelf</hi> with the reſt of our <hi>Company</hi> Conſidered what was beſt to be done, whether we ſhould go any further towards them, or Return, divers of us apprehending much danger in Caſe we did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, becauſe the <hi>Indians</hi> kept not promiſe there with us: But the <hi>three men</hi> who belonged to <hi>Brookfield</hi> were ſo ſtrongly perſwaded of their Freedome from any ill Intentions towards us, (as upon other grounds, ſo eſpecially becauſe the greateſt part of thoſe <hi>Indians</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to <hi>David</hi> one of their <hi>chief Sachems,</hi> who was taken to be a great Friend to the <hi>Engliſh:</hi>) That the ſaid <hi>Captain Hutchinſon</hi> (who was principally Intruſted with the matter of Treaty with
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:136195:5"/>them) was thereby encouraged to proceed and march forward to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a <hi>Swampe</hi> where the <hi>Indians</hi> then were. When we came near the ſaid <hi>Swampe,</hi> the way was ſo very bad that we could march only in a fingle File, there being a very <hi>Rocky Hill</hi> on the right hand, and a <hi>thick Swampe</hi> on the left. In which there were many of thoſe <hi>cruel blood-thirſty Heathen,</hi> who there way-laid us, waiting an opportunity to cut us off; there being alſo <hi>much bruſh</hi> on the ſide of the ſaid <hi>Hill,</hi> where they lay in <hi>Ambuſh</hi> to ſurprize us. When we had marched there about <hi>ſixty or ſeventy Rods,</hi> the ſaid <hi>perfidious Indians</hi> ſent out their ſhot upon us as <hi>a ſhowre of haile,</hi> they being (as was ſuppoſed) about <hi>two hundred men</hi> or more. We ſeeing our ſelves ſo beſet, and not having room to fight, Endeavoured to <hi>fly</hi> for the ſafety of our lives. In which <hi>Flight</hi> we were in no ſmall danger to be all Cut off, there being a very <hi>miry Swamp</hi> before us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which we could not enter with our horſes to go forwards, and there being no ſafety in retreating the way we came, becauſe many of our Enemies, who lay behind the <hi>Buſhes,</hi> and had let us paſs by them quietly; when others had ſhot, they came out, and <hi>ſtopt our way back:</hi> ſo that we were forced as we could to get up the <hi>ſteep and Rocky Hill:</hi> But the greater our danger was, the greater was <hi>Gods mercy in the preſervation of ſo many of us from ſudden deſtruction.</hi> My ſelf being gone up part of the Hill without any hurt, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving ſome of my men to be fallen by the Enemies ſhot: I wheeled about upon the <hi>Indians,</hi> not calling on my men who were left to Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company me, which they in all probability would have done had they known of my Return upon the Enemy. They firing violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of the <hi>Swamp,</hi> and from behind the buſhes on the Hill ſide <hi>wounded me ſorely, and ſhot my Horſe</hi> under me, ſo that he <hi>faultring</hi> and <hi>Falling,</hi> I was forced to leave him, divers of the <hi>Indians</hi> being then but a <hi>few Rods distant</hi> from me, My Son <hi>Thomas Wheeler</hi> flying with the reſt of the Company miſſed me amongſt them, and fearing that I was either ſlain, or much endangered returned towards the <hi>Swampe</hi> again, though he had then received a dangerous wound in the <hi>Reins;</hi> where he ſaw me in the danger aforeſaid: Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he endeavoured to <hi>Reſcue me,</hi> ſhewing himſelf therein a <hi>loving and dutiful Son,</hi> he adventuring himſelf into great peril of his Life to help me in that diſtreſs, there being many of the Enemies about him.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:136195:6"/>My Son ſet me on his own horſe, and ſo eſcaped a while on Foot himſelf, until he Caught an Horſe whoſe Rider was ſlain, on which he mounted, and ſo through <hi>Gods great mercy we both eſcaped:</hi> But in this Attempt for my deliverance he received another dangerous wound by their ſhot in his left Arm. There were then ſlain to out great grief eight men <hi>viz. Zechariah Philips</hi> of <hi>Boſton, Timothy Farlow</hi> of <hi>Billericay, Edward Coleborn</hi> of <hi>Chelmſford, Samuel Smed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> of <hi>Concord, Sydrach Hopgood</hi> of <hi>Sudbury, Serjeant Eyres, Serjeant Prichard,</hi> and <hi>Corporal Coy</hi> the Inhabitants of <hi>Brookfield</hi> aforeſaid; It being the good pleaſure of God, that they ſhould all there fall by their hands, of whoſe good Intentions they were ſo Confident, and whom they ſo little miſtruſted. There were alſo then five perſons wounded, <hi>viz. Captain Hutchinſon, my ſelf,</hi> and my Son <hi>Thomas</hi> as aforeſaid, <hi>Corporal French</hi> of <hi>Billericay,</hi> who having killed an <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> was (as he was taking up his gun) ſhot, and part of one of his <hi>Thumbs taken off;</hi> and alſo dangerouſly wounded through the <hi>Body</hi> near the <hi>Shoulder,</hi> the fifth was <hi>John Waldoe</hi> of <hi>Chelmsford,</hi> who was not ſo dangerouſly wounded as the reſt; They alſo then killed <hi>five</hi> of our horſes, and wounded ſome more, which ſoon died after they came to <hi>Brookfield</hi> Upon this ſudden and unexpected blow gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us (wherein we deſire to look higher then man the Inſtrument) we returned to the Town as faſt as the badneſs of the way, and the weakneſs of our wounded men would permit, we being then Ten Miles from it. All the while we were going we durſt not ſtay to <hi>ſtanch</hi> the <hi>bleeding</hi> of our <hi>wounded men,</hi> for fear the Enemy ſhould have ſurprized us again, which they attempted to do, and had in probability done, but that we perceiving which way they went, wheeled off to the other hand, and ſo by <hi>Gods good Providence to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us,</hi> they miſſed us, and we all came readily upon, and ſafely to the Town, though none of us knew the way to it, thoſe of the place being ſlain as aforeſaid, and we avoiding any thick woods and riding in open places to prevent danger by them. Being got to the Town we ſpeedily betook our ſelves to one of the <hi>largest and ſtrongeſt hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes therein,</hi> where we fortified our ſelves in the beſt manner we could in ſuch <hi>ſtraits of Time,</hi> and there reſolved to <hi>keep Garriſon,</hi> though we were but few, and meanly fitted to make Reſiſtance againſt ſo many Enemies. The News of the <hi>Indians Treacherous dealing</hi> with
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:136195:6"/>us, and the loſs of ſo many of our Company thereby, did ſo <hi>amaze the Inhabitants of the Town,</hi> that they being informed thereof by us preſently left their houſes, divers of them carrying very little away with them, they being afraid of the <hi>Indians</hi> ſudden coming upon them: and ſo came to the houſe we were entred into, very meanly provided of Cloathing, or furniſhed with Proviſions.</p>
            <p>I perceiving my ſelf to be diſenabled for the diſcharge of the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of my place by reaſon of the wound I had received, and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending that the Euemy would ſoon come to ſpoyle the Town, and Aſſault us in the houſe, I appointed <hi>Simon Davis</hi> of <hi>Concord, James Richardſon,</hi> and <hi>John Fiske</hi> of <hi>Chelmsford</hi> to manage Affairs for our Safety with thoſe few men whom God hath left us, and were fit for any Service, and the Inhabitants of the ſaid Town; who did well and Commendably perform the duties of the Truſt committed to them with much Courage and Reſolution through the Aſſiſtance of our gracious God who did not leave us in out low and diſtreſſed ſtate, but did mercifully appear for us in our greateſt need, as in the Sequel will clearly be manifeſted. Within two hours after our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſaid houſe, or leſs, the ſaid <hi>Captain Hutchinſon</hi> and <hi>my ſelf</hi> poſted away <hi>Ephraim Curtis</hi> of <hi>Sudbury,</hi> and <hi>Henry Young</hi> of <hi>Concord</hi> to go to the <hi>Honoured Council</hi> at <hi>Boſton</hi> to give them an Account of the Lords dealings with us, and our preſent Condition. When they came to the further end of the Town they ſaw the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my <hi>Rifling of houſes</hi> which the Inhabitants had forſaken. The <hi>Poſt</hi> fired upon them, and immediately returned to us again, they diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no ſafety in going forward, and being deſirous to inform us of the <hi>Enemies Actings,</hi> that we might the more prepare for a <hi>ſudden Aſſault</hi> by them. Which indeed preſently followed, for as ſoon as the ſaid <hi>Poſt</hi> was come back to us, the <hi>Barbarous Heathen</hi> preſſed upon us in the houſe with great violence, <hi>ſending in their Shot</hi> amongſt us like haile through the walls, and ſhouting as if they would have <hi>ſwallowed us up alive;</hi> but our good God wrought wonderful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for us, ſo that there was but one man wounded within the houſe, <hi>viz</hi> the ſaid <hi>Henry Young</hi> who looking out at a <hi>garret window</hi> that Evening was <hi>mortally wounded</hi> by a Shot, of which wound he died within two dayes after. There was the ſame day another man ſlain, but not in the houſe, a Son of <hi>Serjeant Prichards</hi> adventuring out of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:136195:7"/>the houſe wherein we were, to his Fathers houſe not far from it, to fetch more goods out of it, was Caught by thoſe Cruel Enemies as they were coming towards us, who cut off his head, kicking it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout like a <hi>Foot-ball,</hi> and then putting it upon a <hi>Pole,</hi> they ſet it up before the <hi>door</hi> of his <hi>Fathers houſe</hi> in our ſight.</p>
            <p>The night following the ſaid blow, they did <hi>roar againſt us</hi> like ſo many <hi>wild Bulls,</hi> ſending in their Shot amongſt us till towards the <hi>Moon riſing,</hi> which was about <hi>three of the Clock;</hi> at which time they <hi>Attempted to fire our houſe</hi> by Hay and other Combuſtible matter which they brought to one Corner of the houſe, and ſet it on fire. Whereupon ſome of our Company were neceſſitated to expoſe themſelves to very great danger to put it out: <hi>Simon Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis</hi> one of the three appointed by my ſelf as <hi>Captain,</hi> to ſupply my place by Reaſon of my wounds as aforeſaid, he being of a lively Spirit encouraged the Souldiers within the houſe to <hi>fire upon the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians;</hi> and alſo thoſe that Adventured out to put out the Fire (which began to rage and kindle upon the houſe ſide) with theſe and the like words, That <hi>God is with us, and fights for us, and will deliver us</hi> out of the hands of theſe Heathen; which Expreſſions of his the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians</hi> hearing, they <hi>ſhouted and ſcoffed</hi> ſaying: now ſce how <hi>your God delivers you,</hi> or <hi>will deliver you,</hi> ſending in many ſhots whilſt our men were putting out the Fire. But the Lord of Hoſts wrought ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry graciouſly for us, in preſerving our Bodies both within and without the houſe from their <hi>ſhot,</hi> and our houſe from being <hi>conſumed by Fire,</hi> we had but <hi>two men</hi> wounded in that Attempt of theirs, but we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended that we killed divers of our Enemies. I being deſirous to haſten Intelligence to the <hi>Honoured Council</hi> of our preſent <hi>great distreſs,</hi> we being ſo remote from <hi>any ſuccour,</hi> (It being between <hi>ſixty</hi> and <hi>ſeventy miles</hi> from us to <hi>Boston,</hi> where the <hi>Council</hi> uſeth to ſit) and fearing our <hi>Ammunition</hi> would not laſt long to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them, if they continued ſo to Aſſault us, I ſpak: to <hi>Ephraim Curtis</hi> to adventure forth again on that Service, and to Attempt it on Foot, as the way wherein there was moſt hope of getting away un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcovered; He <hi>readily Aſſented,</hi> and accordingly went out, but there were ſo many <hi>Indians</hi> every where thereabouts, that he could not paſs, without apparent <hi>hazard of Life,</hi> ſo he came back again, yet towards morning the ſaid <hi>Ephraim</hi> adventured forth the <hi>third
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:136195:7"/>time,</hi> and was fain to <hi>creep on his hands and knees</hi> for ſome ſpace of ground, that he might not be diſcerned by the Enemy, who waited to prevent our ſending if they could have hindred it. But through Gods mercy he eſcaped their hands, and got ſafely to <hi>Marlborough,</hi> though very much ſpent, and ready to ſaint by Reaſon of want of ſleep before he went from us, and his ſore travel <hi>night and day</hi> in that <hi>hot Seaſon</hi> till he got thither, from whence he went to <hi>Boſton.</hi> yet before the ſaid <hi>Ephraim</hi> got to <hi>Marlborough,</hi> there was Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence brought thither of the burning of ſome houſes, and killing ſome Cattel at <hi>Quahaug</hi> by ſome who were going to <hi>Connecticut,</hi> but they ſeeing what was done at the End of the Town, and hearing ſeveral guns ſhot off further within the Town, they durſt proceed no further, but Immediately returned to <hi>Marlborough,</hi> though they then know not what had befallen <hi>Captain Hutchinſon and my ſelf, and Company,</hi> nor of our being there, but that timely Intelligence they gave before <hi>Ephraim Curtis</hi> his coming to <hi>Marlborough,</hi> occaſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Honoured <hi>Major Willards</hi> turning his <hi>March</hi> towards <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haug</hi> for our Relief, who were in no ſmall danger every hour of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſtroyed; the ſaid <hi>Major</hi> being when he had that Intelligence upon his <hi>March</hi> another way as he was Ordered by the <hi>Honoured Council,</hi> as is afterwards more fully expreſſed.</p>
            <p>The next day being <hi>Auguſt 3d.</hi> they continued <hi>ſhooting</hi> &amp; <hi>ſhout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> &amp; proceeded in their <hi>former wickedneſs blaſpheming the Name of the Lord,</hi> and <hi>reproaching</hi> us <hi>his Afflicted Servants,</hi> ſcoffing at out <hi>prayers</hi> as they were ſending in their <hi>ſhot</hi> upon all quarters of the houſe And many of them went to the Towns <hi>meeting houſe</hi> (which was within <hi>twenty Rods</hi> of the houſe in which we were) who mocked ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Come and pray, &amp; ſing Pfalms,</hi> &amp; in Contempt made an hideous noiſe <hi>ſomewhat reſembling ſinging.</hi> But we to our power did endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour our own defence, ſending our ſhot amongſt them the Lord giving us Courage to reſiſt them, &amp; preſerving us from the deſtruction they ſought to bring upon us. On the Evening following we ſaw our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Carrying ſeveral of their <hi>dead</hi> or <hi>wounded men</hi> on their <hi>Backs,</hi> who proceeded that night to ſend in their ſhot as they had done the night before, &amp; alſo ſtill ſhouted as if the day had been certainly theirs, and they ſhould without fail, have prevailed againſt us which they might have the more hopes of in regard that we <hi>diſcerned the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:136195:8"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:136195:8"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:136195:9"/>coming of new Companies to them</hi> to Aſſiſt and ſtrengthen them, and the unlikelihood of any coming to our help. They alſo uſed ſeveral <hi>Stratagems to Fire us,</hi> namely by <hi>wild fire</hi> in <hi>Cotton</hi> and <hi>Linnen Rags</hi> with <hi>Brimſtone</hi> in them, which Rags they tyed to the <hi>Piles of their Arrows</hi> ſharp for the purpoſe, and ſhot them to the Roof of our houſe, after they had <hi>ſet them on Fire,</hi> which would have much endangered the burning thereof, had we not uſed means by cutting <hi>holes through the Roof,</hi> and otherwiſe, to beat the ſaid <hi>Arrows</hi> down, and God being pleaſed to proſper our Indeavours therein. They carryed more <hi>Combuſtible matter</hi> as <hi>Flax</hi> and <hi>Hay</hi> to the ſides of the houſe, &amp; ſet it on fire, &amp; then <hi>flocked apace</hi> towards the door of the houſe, either to prevent our going forth to quench the Fire, as we had done before, or to <hi>kill our men</hi> in their Attempt to go forth; or elſe to <hi>break into the houſe by the door;</hi> whereupon we were forced to break down the <hi>wall</hi> of the houſe againſt the <hi>Fire</hi> to <hi>put it out:</hi> They alſo ſhot a <hi>Ball of wild Fire</hi> into the <hi>garret</hi> of the <hi>houſe</hi> which fell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt a great heap of <hi>Flax or Tow</hi> therein; which one of our Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers through Gods good Providence ſoon <hi>eſpyed,</hi> &amp; having <hi>water ready</hi> preſently quenched it; and ſo we were preſerved by the <hi>keeper of Iſrael,</hi> both our <hi>Bodies from their ſhot,</hi> which they ſent thick againſt us, and the <hi>houſe from being conſumed to Aſhes,</hi> although we were but weak to defend our ſelves, we being not above <hi>twenty and ſix men</hi> with thoſe of that ſmall Town, who were able for any Service, and our Enemies as I Judged them about (if not above) <hi>three hundred,</hi> I ſpeak of the leaſt, for many there preſent did gueſs them to be <hi>four or five hundred.</hi> It is the more to be obſerved that ſo little hurt ſhould be done by the Enemies ſhot, it commonly piercing the walls of the houſe, and flying amongſt the People, and there being in the houſe <hi>fifty women and Children</hi> beſides the men before mentioned. But abroad in the yard one <hi>Thomas Wilſon</hi> of that Town being ſent to ſetch water for our help in further need, (that which we had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpent in putting out the Fire) was ſhot by the Enemy in the <hi>upper Jaw,</hi> and in the neck, the anguiſh of which wound was ſuch at the firſt that he cried out with a <hi>great noiſe,</hi> by Reaſon whereof the <hi>Indians</hi> hearing him <hi>rejoyced and triumphed at it;</hi> But his wound was healed in a ſhort time, praiſed be God.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Wedneſday Auguſt the 4th.</hi> the <hi>Indians</hi> Fortifyed themſelves
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:136195:9"/>at the <hi>meeting houſe,</hi> and the <hi>Barne</hi> belonging to our houſe, which they Fortified both at the <hi>great doors,</hi> and at <hi>both Ends</hi> with <hi>Poſts, Rails, Boards, and Hay</hi> to ſave themſelves from our ſhot. They alſo deviſed other <hi>Stratagems</hi> to fire our houſe on the night follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, namely, they took a <hi>Cart,</hi> and filled it with <hi>Flax, Hay and Candlewood,</hi> and other <hi>Combuſtible matter,</hi> and ſet up <hi>Planks</hi> faſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Cart to ſave themſelves from the danger of our ſhot. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Invention they had to make the more ſure work in burning the houſe. They got many <hi>Poles</hi> of a Conſiderable length and bigneſs, and <hi>ſpliced them together</hi> at the Ends one of another, and made a Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of them about <hi>fourteen Rods long,</hi> ſetting the Poles in two Rows with peils laid croſs over them at the <hi>Front End,</hi> and dividing them ſaid Poles about <hi>three foot</hi> aſunder, and in the ſaid <hi>Front</hi> of this their Carriage they ſet a <hi>Barrel,</hi> having made an <hi>hole</hi> through both Heads, and put an <hi>Axle. Tree</hi> through them, to which they faſtened the ſaid <hi>Poles,</hi> and under every joynt of the <hi>Poles</hi> where they were <hi>ſpliced,</hi> they ſet up a a <hi>pair of Truckle wheeles</hi> to bear up the ſaid Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages, and they <hi>loaded the Front</hi> or fore-end thereof with matter <hi>fit for firing,</hi> as <hi>Hay,</hi> and <hi>Flaxe,</hi> and <hi>Chips,</hi> &amp;c. Two of theſe Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments they prepared, that they might Convey <hi>Fire to the houſe,</hi> with the more ſafety to themſelves, they ſtanding at ſuch a diſtance from our ſhot, whilſt they wheeled them to the houſe: great ſtore of <hi>Arrows</hi> they had alſo prepared to ſhoot fire upon the houſe that night; which we found after they were gone, they having left them there. But the Lord who is a <hi>preſent help in Times of trouble,</hi> and is pleaſed to make his <hi>peoples Extremity his opportunity,</hi> did graciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prevent them of Effecting what they hoped they ſhould have done by the aforeſaid devices, partly by ſending a <hi>ſhowre of Rain</hi> in ſeaſon, whereby the matter prepared being wett would not ſo ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily take Fire as it otherwiſe would have done, and partly by <hi>Aide coming to our help.</hi> For our danger would have been very great that night, had not the <hi>only wiſe God (bleſſed for ever)</hi> been pleaſed to ſend to us about an hour within night the <hi>Worſhipful Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor Willard</hi> with <hi>Captain Parker</hi> of <hi>Groaton,</hi> and <hi>Forty ſix men</hi> more with <hi>five Indians</hi> to relieve us in the <hi>Low Eſtate</hi> into which we were brought; <hi>our Eyes were unto him the holy one of Iſrael;</hi> In him we deſired <hi>to place our Truſt,</hi> hoping that he would in the time of our
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:136195:10"/>
               <hi>great need appear for our deliverance,</hi> and Confound all their plots by which they thought themſelves moſt ſure to prevail againſt us; And God <hi>who comforteth the Afflicted,</hi> as he comforted the holy <hi>Apostle Paul by the coming of</hi> Titus <hi>to him,</hi> ſo he greatly comforted us his diſtreſſed Servants both <hi>Souldiers</hi> and <hi>Town Inhabitants</hi> by the coming of the ſaid <hi>Honoured Major,</hi> and thoſe with him. In whoſe ſo ſoon coming to us the <hi>good Providence of God</hi> did <hi>marveilouſly appear;</hi> For the help that came to us by the <hi>Honoured Councils</hi> order (after the tydings they received by our <hi>Post</hi> ſent to them) came not to us till <hi>Saturday August</hi> 7. in the afternoon, nor ſooner could it well come in regard of their diſtance from us, <hi>i. e.</hi> if we had not had help before that time, we ſee not how we could have held out, the number of the <hi>Indians</hi> ſo encreaſing, and they making ſo many Aſſaults up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, that our Ammunition before that time would have been ſpent, and our ſelves diſenabled for any Reſiſtance, we being but ſew, and alwaies fain to ſtand upon our defence; that we had little time for <hi>Refreſhment of our ſelves either by Food or Sleep;</hi> The ſaid <hi>Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Majors</hi> coming to us ſo ſoon was thus occaſioned; He had a <hi>Commiſſion</hi> from the <hi>Honoured Council</hi> (of which himſelf was one) to look after ſome <hi>Indians</hi> to the <hi>Weſt-ward</hi> of <hi>Lancaſter</hi> and <hi>Groa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> (where he himſelf lived) and to ſecure them, and was upon his <hi>march</hi> towards them on the foreſaid <hi>wedneſday</hi> in the morning, <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt 4th.</hi> When Tydings coming to <hi>Marlborough</hi> by thoſe that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned thither as they were going to <hi>Connecticot,</hi> concerning what they ſaw at <hi>Brookfield</hi> as aforeſaid, ſome of <hi>Marlborough</hi> knowing of the ſaid <hi>Majors</hi> march from <hi>Lancaſter</hi> that morning preſently ſent a <hi>Poſt</hi> to acquaint him with the Information they had received; The <hi>Major</hi> was gone before the <hi>Post</hi> came to <hi>Lancaſter;</hi> but there was one ſpeedily ſent after him, who overtook him about <hi>five or ſix miles</hi> from the ſaid Town; He being acquainted, that it was feared, that <hi>Brookfield</hi> (a ſmall Town of about <hi>fifteen or ſixteen Families</hi>) was either deſtroyed, or in great danger thereof, &amp; conceiving it to require more ſpeed to ſuccont them (if they were not paſt help) then to proceed at preſent, as he before intended, and being alſo very deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous (if it were poſſible) to afford Relief to them, (he being then not above <hi>Thirty Miles</hi> from them) he Immediately <hi>altered his Courſe</hi> and <hi>marched</hi> with his <hi>Company</hi> towards us: and came to us
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:136195:10"/>about an <hi>hour after it was dark</hi> as aboveſaid; though he knew not then, neither of our being there, nor of what had befallen us at the <hi>Swampe</hi> and in the houſe thoſe two dayes before.</p>
            <p>The merciful Providence of God alſo appeared in preventing the danger that the <hi>Honoured Major</hi> and his <hi>Company</hi> might have been in, when they came near to us, for thoſe <hi>Beaſtly men</hi> our <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Skilful to deſtroy,</hi> Indeavoured to prevent any help from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our Relief, and therefore ſent down <hi>Sentinels,</hi> (ſome nearer and ſome further off) the furtheſt about <hi>two miles</hi> from us, who if they ſaw any coming from the <hi>Bay</hi> they might give notice by an <hi>Alarm.</hi> And there were about an <hi>hundred</hi> of them who for the moſt part kept at an houſe ſome little diſtance from us, by which if any help came from the ſaid <hi>Bay,</hi> they muſt paſs, and ſo they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended (as we conceive) having notice by their <hi>Sentinels</hi> of their approach to <hi>way-lay them,</hi> and if they could, to <hi>cut them off</hi> before they came to the houſe where we kept.</p>
            <p>But as we propably gueſs, they were ſo intent and buiſy in prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their Inſtruments (as aboveſaid) for our deſtruction by Fire, that they were not at the houſe where they uſed to keep for the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe aforeſaid, and that they heard not their <hi>Sentinels</hi> when they <hi>ſhot;</hi> and ſo the <hi>Majors</hi> way was clear from danger till he came to our houſe. And that it was their purpoſe ſo to have fallen upon him, or any other coming to us at that houſe, is the more propable in that (as we have ſince had Intelligence from ſome of the <hi>Indians</hi> themſelves) there were a party of them at <hi>another place</hi> who <hi>let him paſt by them</hi> without the leaſt hurt or Oppoſition, waiting for a <hi>blow to be given</hi> him at the ſaid <hi>houſe,</hi> and then they themſelves to fall upon them in the <hi>Reare,</hi> as they intended to have done with us at the <hi>Swamp,</hi> in Caſe we had <hi>fled back</hi> as is before expreſſed, The <hi>Major</hi> &amp; <hi>Company</hi> were no ſooner come to the houſe, and underſtood (though at firſt they knew not they were <hi>Engliſh</hi> who were in the houſe, but thought that they might be <hi>Indians,</hi> and therefore were ready to have ſhot at us, till we diſcerning they were <hi>Engliſh</hi> by the <hi>Majors</hi> ſpeaking, I cauſed the <hi>Trumpet to be ſounded</hi>) that the ſaid <hi>Captain Hutchinſon, my ſelf, and Company</hi> with the <hi>Towns Inhabitants</hi> were there, but the <hi>Indians</hi> alſo diſcerned that there were ſome come to cur Aſſiſtance, whereupon they ſpared not their ſhot, but poured it
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:136195:11"/>out on them; but through the Lords goodneſs, though they ſtood not farr aſunder one from another, they <hi>killed not one man,</hi> wounded on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>two</hi> of his Company; and killed the <hi>Majors Sons horſe;</hi> after that we within the houſe perceived the <hi>Indians</hi> ſhooting ſo at them, we haſtened the <hi>Major</hi> and all his Company into the houſe as faſt as we could, and their horſes into a little yard before the houſe, where they wounded <hi>five other horſes</hi> that night; After they were come into the houſe to us, the <hi>Enemies</hi> continued their ſhooting ſome Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable time, ſo that we may well ſay, <hi>had not the Lord been on our ſide when theſe Cruel Heathens roſe up againſt us, they had then ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed us up quick,</hi> when their wrath was kindled againſt us. But <hi>wherein they dealt proudly, the Lord was above them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When they ſaw their <hi>divers deſignes unſucceſsful,</hi> and their hopes therin diſappointed, they then fired the <hi>houſs</hi> &amp; <hi>barne</hi> (wherein they had before kept to lye in wait to ſurprize any coming to us) that by the Light thereof they might the better direct their ſhot at us, but <hi>no hurt</hi> was done thereby <hi>praiſed be the Lord.</hi> And not long after they burnt the <hi>Meeting houſe</hi> wherein their Fortifications were, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the <hi>Barne</hi> which belonged to our houſe, and ſo perceiving more ſtrength come to our Aſſiſtance: they did as we ſuppoſe, <hi>deſpaîr of effecting</hi> any more miſchief againſt us. And therefore the greateſt part of them towards the breaking of the day <hi>Auguſt the fifth</hi> went away and left us, and we were quiet from any further moleſtations by them; and on that morning we went forth of the houſe without danger, and ſo daily afterward, only one man was wounded about two dayes after, as he went out to look after horſes by ſome few of them <hi>ſculking</hi> thereabouts. We cannot tell how many of them we killed in all that time, but one that afteewards was taken confeſſed that there were killed and wounded about <hi>eighty men</hi> or more: <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be the Lord God of our Salvation</hi> who kept us from being all a <hi>prey to their Teeth.</hi> But before they went away they <hi>burnt all the Town</hi> except the houſe we kept in, and another that was not then finiſhed. They alſo made great ſpoyle of the Cattel belonging to the Inhabitants; and after our Entrance into the houſe, and during the time of our <hi>Confinement</hi> there, they either killed or drove away almoſt all the horſes of our Company.</p>
            <p>We Continued there both well and wounded towards a <hi>Fortnight,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:136195:11"/>and <hi>Auguſt the thirteenth Captain Hutchinſon and my ſelf</hi> with the moſt of thoſe that had eſcaped without hurt, and alſo ſome of the wounded came from thence; my Son <hi>Thomas</hi> and ſome other wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men came not from thence, being not then able to endure Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel ſo farr as we were from the next Town, till about a <hi>Fortnight</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. We came to <hi>Marlborough</hi> on <hi>Auguſt the Fourteenth,</hi> where <hi>Captain Hutchinſon</hi> being not recovered of his wound before his coming from <hi>Brookfield,</hi> and overtyred with his <hi>long Journy</hi> by Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his weakneſs quickly after grew worſe, and more dangerouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ill, and on the <hi>nineteenth day</hi> of the ſaid moneth dyed, and was there the day after buried, the Lord being pleaſed to deny him a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to his own habitation, and his near Relations at <hi>Boſton,</hi> though he was come the greateſt part of his Journy thitherward. The In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the <hi>Town</hi> alſo not long after, <hi>men, women,</hi> and <hi>Children,</hi> removed ſafely with what they had left to ſeveral places, either where they had lived before their planting or ſitting down there; or where they had Relations to receive and entertain them. The Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured <hi>Major Willard</hi> ſtayed at <hi>Brookfield</hi> ſome weeks after our coming away, there being ſeveral Companies of Souldiers ſent up thither and to <hi>Hadly</hi> and the Towns thereabouts, which are about <hi>Thirty Miles</hi> from <hi>Brookfield,</hi> whither alſo the <hi>Major</hi> went for a time upon the Service of the Country in the preſent warr, and from whence there being need of his preſence for the ordering of matters concerning his own <hi>Regiment</hi> and the ſafety of the <hi>Towns</hi> belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to it, he through Gods goodneſs and mercy returned in ſafety and health to his houſe, and dear Relations at <hi>Groaton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus I have Indeavoured to ſet down and declare both what the Lord did againſt us in the Loſs of ſeveral perſons Lifes, and the wounding of others, ſome of which wounds were very painful in dreſſing, and long ere they were healed, beſides many dangers that we were in, and fears that we were exerciſed with; and alſo what great things he was pleaſed to do for us in fruſtrating their many At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, and vouchſafing ſuch a Deliverance to us. The Lord <hi>avenge the Blood that hath been ſhed</hi> by theſe <hi>Heathen</hi> who <hi>hate us without a Cauſe,</hi> though he be moſt Righteous in all that hath befallen there, and in all other parts of the Country; He help us to <hi>humble our ſelves</hi> before him, and with our <hi>whole hearts to return to him,</hi> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:136195:12"/>to improve all his mercies which we ſtill enioy, that ſo his <hi>anger may ceaſe</hi> towards us and he may be pleaſed either to make our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies at <hi>peace with us,</hi> or more, <hi>deſtroy them</hi> before us I tarried at <hi>Marl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough</hi> with <hi>Captain Hutchinſon</hi> until his death, and came home to <hi>Concord Auguſt the</hi> 21. (though not throughly recovered of my wound) and ſo did others that went with me. But ſince I am Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable well, though I have not the uſe of my hand and Arm as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: My Son <hi>Thomas</hi> though in great <hi>hazard of Life</hi> for ſome time after his return to <hi>Concord,</hi> yet is now very well Cured, and his ſtrength well reſtored.! <hi>Oh that we could praiſe the Lord for his great goodneſs towards us.</hi> Praiſed be his Name, that though he took away ſome of us, yet was pleaſed to ſpare ſo many of us, and adde unto our dayes; He help us <hi>whoſe Souls he hath delivered from Death, and Eyes from Tears, and Feet from falling to walk before him in the Land of the Living</hi> till our great Change come, and to <hi>ſanctifie his Name</hi> in all <hi>his wayes</hi> about us, that both our Afflictions, and our mercies may quicken us to live more to his glory all our dayes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:136195:12"/>
            <head>THE SERNON</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Pſal. <hi>116.12.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>What ſhall I Render unto the Lord for all his Benefits towards me.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is no Condition of men here below ſo good, but there is <hi>need of duty;</hi> There is none ſo bad, as to be <hi>paſt duty.</hi> In all Eſtates we muſt be doing: no <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence</hi> exempts from <hi>duty;</hi> yet <hi>ſeveral Conditions</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire ſeveral duties; The Chriſtian Converſation is like a <hi>wheel</hi> every <hi>Spoke taketh its Turn;</hi> God hath planted in man <hi>Affections</hi> for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Condition; <hi>grace</hi> for every <hi>Affection,</hi> and a <hi>duty</hi> for the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of every grace, and a <hi>Seaſon</hi> for every <hi>duty;</hi> in which it is moſt <hi>beautiful;</hi> In the day of Trouble and Affliction, the duty then is <hi>Prayer and Petition;</hi> In the time of Deliverance and Proſperity <hi>Thanksgiving; giving praiſe to the God of our Salvation;</hi> and it is wiſdome to perform what is moſt ſeaſonable, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.13. <hi>Is any Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, let him pray?</hi> Aske mercy and deliverance from the evils at Gods hand. Is any merry by Reaſon of mercy received, <hi>let him ſing Pſalms of praiſe?</hi> exalting the Lord for his free goodneſs and bounty therein.</p>
            <p>Accordingly the holy Prophet (very probably <hi>David</hi>) in this Pſalm ſets before us the Exerciſe of his grace in various Conditions which befell him: He tels us what he did in the time of great <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction and Diſtreſs;</hi> he prayed, <hi>He called upon the Name of the Lord: ver.</hi> 3, 4. and being delivered and helped what he did, and was reſolved to do: <hi>He loved the Lord,</hi> and would <hi>walk before him in the Land of the Living;</hi> He was thankful, and would expreſs his <hi>gratitude</hi> in his <hi>Converſation;</hi> yea, is Inquiſitive, what further to do
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:136195:13"/>therein; as in the Text, <hi>what ſhall I Render,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The Pſalm then is <hi>Euchariſtical;</hi> or <hi>Gratulatory,</hi> wherein the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> giveth praiſe to God for his <hi>favour</hi> and <hi>mercy</hi> in a great <hi>Deliverance</hi> from a <hi>deadly danger</hi> and <hi>diſtreſs;</hi> and ſo ſuitable to the preſent occaſion of our meeting at this time; If <hi>David</hi> were the Penman thereof, the Deliverance may be that mentioned, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18. Title: His preſervation from <hi>Sauls furious</hi> and <hi>malicious Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and the rage and violence of all his Adherents, and all others that ſought his Ruine.</p>
            <p>The words read contein a <hi>Pathetical Exclamation</hi> and <hi>Enquiry; what ſhall I render,</hi> &amp;c. as if he ſhould ſay; The Lord hath beſtowed <hi>mercies,</hi> yea, many and great mercies upon me; He hath <hi>heard my prayer</hi> when the <hi>ſorrows of death encompaſſed me, helped me</hi> when I was <hi>brought very low;</hi> ſomething is to be returned to him, that even Reaſon ſuggeſts, yea, much is to be done; but what that is I am (as it were) at a Loſs, I would do any thing to pleaſe and honour him, who hath done ſo much for me.</p>
            <div type="analysis">
               <head>In the words there are <hi>two parts.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. An <hi>Inquiſition;</hi> wherein we may Conſider: 1. The <hi>Subject</hi> or matter enquired after: <hi>what ſhall I render: 2dly.</hi> The <hi>Object</hi> or perſon concerning whom the Enquiry is made, and to whom the Return is to be made, and that is <hi>Jehovah;</hi> Not man but <hi>the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly,</hi> The Reaſon of the <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> and that is the Conſideration of <hi>all his Benefits;</hi> There was juſt occaſion to be ſo ſollicitous; <hi>Gods Benefits,</hi> ſet out, 1. <hi>By an Amplification</hi> All, <hi>All his Benefits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly, By an Application,</hi> towards me; All his Benefits <hi>towards me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this verſe we have the <hi>Queſtion,</hi> In the verſes following we have the <hi>Reſolution;</hi> He will <hi>take the Cup of Salvation,</hi> &amp;c. and He will <hi>pay the Vows</hi> which he had made in his Trouble and Diſtreſs.</p>
               <p>For Explication of the Terms <hi>[Render]</hi> The word Imports a kind of <hi>Requital;</hi> It is attributed both to God and man, and that in Relation to a good thing done, and ſignifies to reward, and to an Evil, and ſignifies to <hi>Revenge:</hi> Here it is Attributed to <hi>man in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to God,</hi> but not as importing any poſſibility and ſatisfaction,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:136195:13"/>but only a <hi>readineſs</hi> and <hi>forwardneſs</hi> to do any thing that might be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>[Benefits]</hi> The word in the <hi>Original</hi> is derived of that Verb which in the <hi>ſeventh verſe</hi> is Tranſlated <hi>[dealt bountifully]</hi> Gods Bounties: And theſe the Prophet ſtiles <hi>His Benefits,</hi> acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the good he received to come from him.</p>
               <p>The Verſe then is a Deſcription of the frame of heart of a <hi>faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Thanksgiver.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. In his <hi>Obſervation</hi> of Gods diſpenſation towards him, in the <hi>Benefits beſtowed on him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly,</hi> In his <hi>Sollicitouſneſs</hi> what to do by way of <hi>Retribution,</hi> and his willingneſs to do whatſoever he knows may be acceptable to him and approved by him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="doctrine">
               <head>Hence this Doctrine may be raiſed.</head>
               <p>Doct. <hi>A perſon or people in a right thankful frame upon the Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Gods Benifits, and Bountiful favours towards them, are very Sollicitous what to return to God for them.</hi> Or ſuch <hi>as are after Gods heart upon their Obſervation of mercies and deliverances beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on them are Sollicitous what Returns to make to God for them:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There be two parts in the Doctrine. 1. That a gracious Heart <hi>obſerves</hi> and takes notice of Gods goodneſs towards him. <hi>2dly,</hi> He is thereupon <hi>Inquiſitive</hi> what to <hi>Return</hi> to God.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Prophet takes notice of Gods goodneſs; His <hi>Inquiſition</hi> what to return, for it argues his <hi>Obſervation</hi> of it; If he enquires <hi>what to Render,</hi> It argues his taking notice of the <hi>Benefits;</hi> yea, of the <hi>variety and multitude</hi> of them, in what God had been doing for him. So <hi>David</hi> tels us <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.14. <hi>marveilous are thy works and that my Soul knoweth right well.</hi> So alſo in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.1, to the <hi>ſixth verſe, Neh.</hi> 9.7, to <hi>27th verſe:</hi> They take notice of the great and manifold mercies which God had beſtowed upon his people <hi>Iſrael</hi> in former as well as latter times. The Reaſons hereof are.</p>
               <p>Reaſon 1. <hi>From the worth of every one of Gods mercies.</hi> There is not one of <hi>All</hi> of Gods <hi>Benefits,</hi> and the bleſſings which we enjoy but it is worthy of <hi>notice,</hi> for it is the <hi>Lords work;</hi> the <hi>Operation of his hands,</hi> every mercy is Gods gift, and therefore to be Eyed and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111.2. <hi>The works of the Lord are great, ſought out of all them that have pleaſure therein.</hi> As your deliverance from the great
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:136195:14"/>danger you were in at the <hi>Swampe,</hi> and afterwards in the Houſe: It's worthy <hi>obſerving</hi> and <hi>remembring:</hi> how much more, <hi>All our mercies</hi> at all time and in all places. All comes from God, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Every good and perfect gift commeth,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Reaſon 2. <hi>From the Thankfulneſs we owe to God</hi> for every mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy being <hi>unworthy of the least of them;</hi> as <hi>Gen.</hi> 32 10. <hi>Jacob</hi> hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly acknowledgeth. Now, how ſhall we be Thankful for them if we do not obſerve them. Hence the Prophet to Induce men to <hi>Thankfulneſs,</hi> and to bleſs God for his goodneſs and mercy adviſeth men to take notice of his kindneſs towards them: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 100.3, 4. And when the Lord upbraids his people for their great Ingratitude towards him, he gives this as one Cauſe of it, and ſo expreſſeth it, <hi>they did not know nor Conſider, Iſai.</hi> 1.3. and <hi>Hoſ:</hi> 2.8. <hi>ſhe did not know that I gave,</hi> &amp;c that is, ſhe did not ſeriouſly <hi>Conſider</hi> of it, that thereby ſhe might have been ſtirred up to <hi>Thankfolneſs</hi> in obedience.</p>
               <p>Reaſon 3. <hi>From the great difficulty of raiſing up our dull and ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſh hearts to that great duty of praiſe and Thankfulneſs,</hi> eſpecially, in a lively and ſpiritual frame; and therefore there is great need to obſerve not only ſome, but <hi>All his Benefits:</hi> Though <hi>one mercy</hi> ſhould raiſe our Hearts to Heaven; yet the more to quicken and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large them, we ſhould take notice of <hi>All;</hi> the variety of them; as praiſe is a <hi>difficult duty,</hi> ſo it is difficult raiſing our hearts to the <hi>du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> We are <hi>dull and Listleſs</hi> to all duty, but eſpecially to <hi>Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs;</hi> We are <hi>ſlow to go to God for mercy</hi> in our Troubles and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes, but more ſlow to <hi>Return praiſe</hi> after <hi>Deliverances</hi> vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed. Hence that Expreſſion in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107. Pſal. 8.15 21, 31. <hi>Oh that men would praiſe the Lord;</hi> as if he ſhould ſay: It's rather to be wiſhed then expected, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.17, 18. There were Ten cried <hi>Lord have mercy upon us,</hi> but only <hi>one Returned to give Thanks</hi> to Jeſus Chriſt when cured.</p>
               <p>The ſecond part of the Doctrine. <hi>Gracious and Humble Hearts obſerving Gods goodneſs towards them, are studious and Sollicitous what to Return to him.</hi> So the Prophet here, <hi>what ſhall I Render to the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. ſo 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.1. when God had brought him to Reſt in his Kingdome after ſo many wandrings; he was ſtudying how to advance the honour of God, who had done ſo great things for him; had ſo delivered him, ſo <hi>advanced him</hi> to <hi>honour and Renown,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:136195:14"/>3.9. what <hi>Thanks</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>can we Render.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="reasons">
               <head>The Reaſons hereof are,</head>
               <p>Reaſon 1. <hi>From the Conſideration of the Nature of the Benefits,</hi> Gods people enjoy; The Prophet here may well ſay, <hi>what ſhall I Render,</hi> &amp;c. and ſo may every Child of God ſay; All that are in Covenant with him; <hi>what ſhall we Render</hi> for the Benefits we have received from our God.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>They are great mercies;</hi> even very great; as the promiſes of good to be given are <hi>great Promiſes,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.4. ſo the good promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and beſtowed. They are <hi>great favours,</hi> eſpecially in <hi>ſpiritual bleſſings.</hi> He gives great Deliverances; as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.50. he doth great Things for his, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 71.19. and 86.13.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly,</hi> They are very many; There is an <hi>All</hi> of them, as in the Text; an <hi>All</hi> that is beyond Expreſſion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.14. <hi>more in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber then the ſand.</hi> There is a multitude of them: This was an Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravation of <hi>Iſraels</hi> ſin, that they <hi>remembred not the multitude of Gods mercies,</hi> Pſal. 106.7.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3dly, They are Everlaſting mercies,</hi> Pſal. 136. In every verſe <hi>thy mercy endures for ever;</hi> Gods people ſee and acknowledge <hi>Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting mercy,</hi> even in outward and temporal bleſſings; much more in ſpiritual and Eternal: Becauſe though the mercies themſelves do not <hi>Indure for ever,</hi> yet the Foundation of all to Gods people is <hi>Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting grace &amp; mercy;</hi> And beſides even theſe do in ſome degree tend to further their <hi>Everlaſting bleſſedneſs;</hi> helping them on in their way to their <hi>Fathers houſe</hi> in heaven; therefore there is Reaſon to ſtudy and be Sollicitous what to render to God for them.</p>
               <p>Reaſon 2. <hi>From the Conſideration of the perſon</hi> from whom the Bleſſings and Deliverances come, and to whom the Return is to be made, and that is, <hi>the Lord,</hi> what ſhall I Render <hi>to the Lord</hi> for His Benefits.</p>
               <p n="1">1. All the good we enjoy is <hi>from the Lord:</hi> we are the <hi>Receivers,</hi> He the <hi>giver.</hi> They are his <hi>Benefits:</hi> yea, the gifts of the <hi>Lord of Lords and King of Kings,</hi> the great and mighty God, who Inhabits the Throne of glory. Oh that the God of glory ſhould have any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to us <hi>duſt and Aſhes,</hi> that he ſhould do ſo great things for us
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:136195:15"/>worthleſs ones; Pſal. 113.5, 6, 7. <hi>who is like unto the Lord our God who dwelleth on High; who humbleth himſelf,</hi> &amp;c. He raiſeth <hi>the poor out of the Duſt,</hi> &amp;c. A good look from a Prince or ſome other great and honourable perſon, is more then a greater thing from a meaner perſon.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly,</hi> Our <hi>Returns are to be made to the Lord,</hi> and therefore we had need be Careful what we preſent to him: This Reaſon God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf gives why he <hi>Curſeth the deceiver</hi> who hath a <hi>male in his Flock,</hi> and offereth to God a <hi>corrupt thing;</hi> becauſe he is a <hi>great King: Mal.</hi> 1.14. and therefore he ſharply reproves them for offering the <hi>halt and blind.</hi> verſ. 8. Perſons are uſually Careful how they carry themſelves towards a great man in returning Thanks to him for favours received from him; much more here ought there to be Care; The Return is to be made to God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Solomon</hi> gives this Reaſon of the <hi>magnificence</hi> of the houſe he was to Build, It was for <hi>the Lord</hi> who is a great and glorious one: 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 2.5. Any manner of houſe would not ſerve the turn, the beſt <hi>Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> and <hi>ſtone</hi> muſt be provided, and it muſt be wrought in the beſt manner, and by the <hi>moſt Skilful perſons</hi> that could be procured. This was <hi>Abels</hi> Commendation, that he brought of the <hi>Firstlings of his Flock</hi> and of the <hi>fat thereof,</hi> Gen. 4.4. and to him God had Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect and to his Offering.</p>
               <p>Reaſon 3. <hi>From the Conſideration of the perſon</hi> that is to make the Return to God; <hi>what ſhall I Return;</hi> I that am ſo <hi>unworthy of the leaſt mercy:</hi> I that have had ſo <hi>many mercies,</hi> ſo great <hi>Deliverances,</hi> I that am notable to Render any thing <hi>beſeeming his Majeſty;</hi> I that am un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſo many <hi>Bonds and Obligations;</hi> I that am ſo <hi>priviledged by God; what ſhall I Render,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Hence that Expreſſion, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17, 18, 19, 20. <hi>What can David ſay,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>David</hi> the youngeſt of all my Fathers Sons, and yet was preferred before them; <hi>David</hi> that was a <hi>Shepard,</hi> and now advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to <hi>Regal dignity; David</hi> that was ſo perſecuted by <hi>potent</hi> and <hi>cruel</hi> Enemies, and hath been ſo graciouſly and wonderfully pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved. This makes a thankful heart <hi>ſtudious,</hi> eſpecially, Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring theſe three things therewith.</p>
               <p n="1">1. All that we can Return is but <hi>little</hi> to his mercies; but <hi>mites</hi> for <hi>Talents; words</hi> for <hi>wonders;</hi> All is as nothing.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:136195:15"/> 
                  <hi>2dly,</hi> What we Return to God is (and by Reaſon of ſin indwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling will be) mixt with many Imperfections; our beſt Services are but as <hi>torne Rags, menstruous Cloaths,</hi> Iſai. 64.6. Even our <hi>Robes,</hi> our beſt Services need waſhing in the <hi>Blood of the Lord,</hi> Revel. 7.14.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3dly,</hi> All that we can give to God is <hi>His own;</hi> and is but little of his own; and therefore the Saints are ſenſible of their own Ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility to make any meet Requital to God. Mark holy <hi>Davids</hi> Expreſſions after <hi>his and the Princes offering</hi> towards the <hi>Building of the Temple,</hi> 1 Chron. 29.10, to 15. <hi>verſ.</hi> a full place to prove all theſe three particulars before mentioned.</p>
               <p>Uſe I. By <hi>way of Inſtruction</hi> or <hi>Information.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Inſtruct. 1. A Soul in a <hi>thankful frame,</hi> in a Tune of Thanksgiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing can never be <hi>ſufficiently ſatisfied</hi> in <hi>thinking</hi> and <hi>ſpeaking</hi> of <hi>Gods mercies</hi> and favours towards him. The Prophet had before in this <hi>Pſalm</hi> ſpoken of Gods goodneſs towards him; acknowledged his <hi>Bounty,</hi> what God had done for him; yea, again and again, repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it: and yet he is here ſtill at the ſame work in the Text: <hi>What ſhall</hi> I <hi>Render,</hi> &amp;c. yea, again, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.17. <hi>How great</hi> hath Gods goodneſs been in <hi>hearing prayer, reſcuing</hi> me from <hi>deadly dangers, helping</hi> me when I was in a <hi>low Estate, delivering mine Eyes from Tears,</hi> &amp;c. beſtowing ſo many <hi>Benefits,</hi> looſing my <hi>bonds,</hi> Pſ. 136. In every verſe, <hi>Thy mercy endureth for ever. Oh praiſe, give thanke for his mercy:</hi> and when he was concluding, he was ready to begin again: <hi>Oh give Thanks,</hi> ver. 26. <hi>Oh give Thanks to the God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> for, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> A thankeful heart in a lively frame takes delight to ſpeak of the goodneſs of God towards him, Is not ſoon tyred nor weary thereof. All <hi>Repetitions</hi> are not babling: and therefore let us beware of ſo judging them; ſometimes out of the Aboundance of the Heart Chriſtians go over and over the ſame thing in <hi>petition</hi> of good from God and in <hi>Thanksgiving</hi> for good received at his hands.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Instruct.</hi> 2. The Lord ſo diſpenſeth mercy to his people, as there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he leads them unto <hi>ſpecial</hi> and <hi>ſolemn ſeaſons of Thanksgiving:</hi> Though he do afflict them, viſit them with Rods, yet in the midſt of thoſe Exerciſes, he ſo diſpenſeth favours that they have Cauſe and juſt occaſion, not only of ordinary, but alſo <hi>Extraordinary praiſes.</hi> Their mercies come in a more then ordinary way, and ſo call for morethen ordinary praiſes.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:136195:16"/>
               <p> Sometimes God giveth them <hi>mercies</hi> through many difficulties, as <hi>water out of the Rock:</hi> Deut. 32.13. which together with their ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity made the water as <hi>bony and Oyle:</hi> God could give them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother way, he goes that way, that thereby he might provoke them to <hi>Thanksgiving:</hi> Divers Inſtances we have in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107. ſome he caſts into <hi>Exile,</hi> and delivers them: others into <hi>Bonds and Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and releaſeth them, others he makes <hi>ſick</hi> and heals them, that they may praiſe him.</p>
               <p>He brings them into great dangers, and Diſtreſſes at <hi>Sea</hi> and <hi>Land,</hi> that they may <hi>Render Praiſe</hi> in their Redemption, Thus hath been Gods diſpenſations towards you here met: you were in great diſtreſs, <hi>i.e.</hi> and he hath not left you without <hi>ſignal Providences,</hi> gracious diſcoveries of mercy: and ſo given you occaſion of <hi>Solemn Thanksgiving.</hi> He brought you <hi>Low,</hi> and hath <hi>raiſed you,</hi> that you might <hi>praiſe him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Inſtruct.</hi> 3. A Thankeful Spirit is a <hi>Reſolute and Inquiſitive Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, Inquiſitive</hi> to know, and <hi>Reſolute</hi> to do what it knoweth may pleaſe the Lord.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is <hi>Inquiſitive</hi> to know <hi>what it may, what it ſhould do:</hi> This is the property of gratefulneſs either to God or man, as in <hi>David</hi> reſpecting the Poſterity of his dear <hi>Jonathan.</hi> Is there any of the houſe of <hi>Saul,</hi> &amp;c. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 9.1. ſo alſo in <hi>Eliſha</hi> reſpecting the <hi>Shu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namite,</hi> who had ſhewed him ſo much kindneſs, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 4.13.14. What is to be <hi>done for her?</hi> Grateful Children and Friends will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to know what may pleaſe their Parents, Friends. And ſo it is with the Children and Friends of God: They deſire to know the mind and will of God what he <hi>requires of them:</hi> and what may be an <hi>acceptable Sacrifice</hi> to him. Hence they pray for <hi>knowledge</hi> and <hi>underſtanding</hi> as <hi>David,</hi> Pſal, 119.33, 34 Hence alſo they will ſearch the word of God, that they may <hi>underſtand his will,</hi> and underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, <hi>do it,</hi> Rom. 12.2.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly.</hi> It is a <hi>Reſolute Spirit</hi> reſolved to do what ever may expreſs the Thankfulneſs of his heart to God, according to his will. As he purpoſeth in his heart <hi>not to ſin</hi> by doing the <hi>Leaſt Evil,</hi> Dan. 1.8 ſo he purpoſeth and reſolveth to do, (though not in his own ſtrength) what is <hi>pleaſing to God,</hi> Pſal. 119.8. <hi>I will keep thy Precepts,</hi> and in the Text, <hi>what ſhall</hi> I <hi>Render,</hi> &amp;c. I will ſtick at nothing, will do
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:136195:16"/>any thing; as when <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſupplyed the <hi>Egyptians</hi> with Come, they yield to any Terms; Let us <hi>find grace in the ſight of my Lord,</hi> and we will be <hi>Pharoahs Servants,</hi> Gen 47 25. And as <hi>David</hi> was ready to do what ever <hi>Barzilla</hi> ſhould requeſt of him, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.38. In teſtimony of his <hi>Thankfulneſs</hi> for his <hi>Loyalty</hi> and <hi>Bounty</hi> at ſuch a time; ſo a gracious Soul much more towards God; It is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to do any thing, to ſuffer any thing whereby God may be honoured. As <hi>Paul,</hi> Acts 21.14. How ungrateful then are they that will not do what they know to be pleaſing to God, though it be clearly ſet before them, and ſtrongly urged on them? <hi>young men</hi> are called upon to <hi>turn to God quickly; elder</hi> and <hi>younger</hi> ones to <hi>ſeek after him</hi> in all his holy Ordinances; to forſake their Luſts and vain Company; but they will not; <hi>they hold faſt deceit</hi> and refuſe to Return.</p>
               <p>They know what is good, but will not do it. Many know their duties in their Relations towards <hi>Superiours</hi> and <hi>Inferiours,</hi> but <hi>will not</hi> yield to them. And though ſome for Carnal ſiniſter Reſpects do many things; as <hi>Jebu, Herod,</hi> &amp;c. yet at ſomething they ſtick; ſome <hi>Dalilah</hi> they will keep, ſome <hi>Lust</hi> they will not part withal, ſome duty they will not perform. Eſpecially how farr are ſuch from Thankfulneſs that reſolve not to do, what God ſets before them: as they, <hi>Jer.</hi> 44.16, 17; The word that <hi>thou haſt ſpoken to us in the Name of the Lord we will not do.</hi> Such are moſt Ingrateful ones for all the mercies they receive from him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Inſtruct. 4th.</hi> To be truly thankful to God is an high, and ave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Spiritual Service; It is a Rendring and making Returns to God: <hi>what ſhall I Render to God,</hi> &amp;c. For man to be ſit to receive from God is a great matter, but it is much higher for us to Render to God, that man duſt and Aſhes ſhould make a Requital to the great and glorious God. Therefore <hi>David</hi> ſo magnifies God that they ſhould offer ſo liberally to him: 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.10, &amp;c. It is a great matter to be admired, that God ſhould honour us, therefore ſaith the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>what is man that thou art mindful of him,</hi> &amp;c, <hi>Thou haſt Crowned him with glory and honour;</hi> but for us to honour God is greater; It is an high duty for the Sons of men, which are but worms to riſe ſo high as to honour God: praiſing of God is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolling or Exalting God, <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.2. He is higher then to be exalted
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:136195:17"/>by us, yet this we are ſaid to do, in an Acknowledgement of his hand, giving him the glory of his wiſdome, power, goodneſs, Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs and mercy in the operations of his hand about us. Think it not an eaſy thing to praiſe the Lord; It is not only a lip labour, an eaſy Service; It is a Rendring to God. To play on Muſick is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, but it is hard to ſet the Inſtrument in Tune to play well; It is hard to get the heart in Tune, in a Spiritual lively, humble frame; Hence <hi>David</hi> ſo ſtirs up himſelf to it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.1, 2, and <hi>Deborab</hi> calls upon her ſelf to awake, <hi>Judg.</hi> 5.12.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Instruct. 5th.</hi> Gods doings are the matter of the Saints Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgements in their Thanksgivings and praiſes of him. The word Tranſlated <hi>Praiſe</hi> ſignifies <hi>Confeſſion</hi> and ſo often Rendred by Mr. <hi>Ainſworth.</hi> Confeſs the Lord, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now the Lords doings are the matter of their Confeſſions: <hi>[his Benefits]</hi> what he hath done for me, and others of his people, the works of his hands for mine and others deliverance and Salvation. When we praiſe the Lord, we do but ſing over what he hath done, He acts it, and we acknowledge it; As in this Salvation vouchſafed to you from the Enemy, from their Attempts by Aſſaults, Fire, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>An <hi>Eccho</hi> is little elſe but a Reflecting Repetition of the firſt ſound; ſo our praiſes are Repetitions, reflecting the work on God; He heard, he helped, he delivered and ſaved; <hi>This is the Lords doings.</hi> There is an <hi>Amen</hi> in Thanksgiving; our <hi>Amen</hi> to the Truth of Gods diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations; we ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to them; ſo they are, and we acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it. To give Thanks is to give God a Tribute in the Confeſſion of his goodneſs; It is Retribution: This is to Crown the Lord, we owne him the Author of all our manifold Comforts, Deliverances, ſupplies in one kind or other. There is a diſtinction made between glory and glorification; glory is an Eſſential Attribute, though there were no Angel or man; but glorification is the acknowledgement of his power, goodneſs, mercy in his works by the Rational Creature.</p>
               <p>What are you then to acknowledge this day? Even the Lords doings in your <hi>marpeilous preſervation:</hi> If you would glorifie him this day then ſay: the Lord hath done great things for us. <hi>This is the Lords doing, and it is wonderful in our Eyes!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Inſtruct. 6th.</hi> One <hi>ſpecial particular mercy</hi> received from God, ought to raiſe up our <hi>Hearts</hi> to a Conſideration of all other mercies
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:136195:17"/>formerly beſtowed on us: And ſo it ſhould be with you meet to praiſe the <hi>Lords glorious Name</hi> for that great Deliverance at the <hi>Swampe,</hi> and in the <hi>Garriſon.</hi> The Prophet addes that general Particle <hi>All,</hi> to ſhew that from that preſent Benefit which God had Conferred on him in that great Deliverance mentioned <hi>verſ.</hi> 2.3. his heart was extended to a Conſideration of other favours which the Lord from time to time had ſhewed him.</p>
               <p>Thus it will be with a <hi>grateful Heart:</hi> Not that we can think on every benefit, ſo as to leave out none, they being ſo Innumerable: but it is to be taken of the ſeveral kinds: as general, particular, publick, private, temporal and Spiritual, and of as many ſeveral and diſtinct branches of theſe as we can, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.2. <hi>Forget not all, nor any of his Benefits,</hi> and <hi>Pſal</hi> 105 2 <hi>Talk you of all his wondrous works.</hi> This is the means to enlarge the heart, and Inflame it with <hi>holy Zeal,</hi> in praiſing God, as more Fuel brought to the fire makes it greater. Here is a good help to this great duty this day, and at other times, obſerve all kinds of mercies, and call to mind what God hath done for you formerly, for your perſons, Families, Relations, for the Churches to which you belong, for the Country.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Inſtruct.</hi> 7. The Conſideration of mercies beſtowed on our ſelves, and our Intereſt in the mercies beſtowed on others is a great means to provoke to Thankfulneſs: ſo the Prophet here. For all his Beneſits towards me. ſo <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.1, to 6. <hi>verſ. Bleſs the Lord O my Soul,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>who forgives all thine iniquities, and beals all thy Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>We are moſt ſenſible of kindneſs done to our ſelves, the ſweet where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of our own Souls taſt, &amp; according to the Senſe and taſt of any kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, is the heart quickned and ſtirred up to Thankfulneſs. Oh take ſpecial notice of ſuch mercies, as in particular concern thy ſelf: For in the Caſe and buiſineſs of your preſent meeting: one may ſay, I was ſpared and not touched, when others were dangeroufly wounded: Another may ſay, I was only wounded, when others were killed: I am recovered, when others wounds proved mortal: God hath given me my Life, when others are taken away by Death: I am returned to my Relations, or my Relations are come home in ſafety, when others have not enjoyed ſuch a mercy.</p>
               <p>Conſider withal, how you are Intereſted in the mercies of others,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:136195:18"/>either particular perſons, or in the <hi>Common</hi> and <hi>publick mercies</hi> of the <hi>Town</hi> and <hi>Country.</hi> You have an Intereſt in the mercies of your <hi>Yoke-fellow, Children.</hi> In the mercies of the <hi>Town, Church ſtate:</hi> If the Town be ſpared (when others are conſumed) It is mercy to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty particular: If <hi>huſband</hi> be returned home ſafe, It is a Benefit to me, <hi>may the wife ſay:</hi> If the <hi>Father</hi> be returned, It is a Benefit to me, <hi>may the Child ſay:</hi> ſo may the <hi>Father</hi> ſay in the <hi>Childs</hi> Return: The mercies in <hi>Magiſtracy,</hi> and <hi>Miniſtry</hi> are our mercies, They are Gods Benefits to us. <hi>ſelf Intereſts</hi> are affecting Intereſts. Conſider how thou art Intereſted in any mercy, Deliverance, Immediately or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, and this will further our Thankfulneſs for it. As this is a way to <hi>affect the Heart</hi> with the <hi>Churches</hi> affliction, to Conſider our <hi>Interest</hi> therein as members of the ſame <hi>Body,</hi> ſo alſo to affect our Hearts with Gods goodneſs to others, to Conſider how we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned therein.</p>
               <p>It may be ſome may ſay, I have more Cauſe to <hi>Faſt and Pray</hi> in regard of Gods hand on me and mine rather then to <hi>Rejoyce</hi> and <hi>Feast:</hi> Do but Conſider thy many perſonal mercies, thy Family mercies, and thy Intereſt in Common-wealth, and Church mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and thou mayeſt ſee aboundant <hi>Cauſe of Thankfulneſs.</hi> It is a Certain Truth, that a Child of God when he is in the worſt Caſe he can be in here upon earth, hath more Cauſe of <hi>Gratulation</hi> then of <hi>Petition.</hi> His <hi>mercies</hi> are greater then his <hi>miſeries:</hi> His <hi>Enjoyments</hi> more then his <hi>wants,</hi> beſides his hopes of all good at laſt in an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable Eſtate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Inſtruct. 8th.</hi> If <hi>Temporal mercies</hi> be carefully to be obſerved, and <hi>Return</hi> made to God for them, how much more for <hi>Spiritual and Eternal mercies</hi> If Deliverance from a <hi>temporal Death,</hi> how much more Deliverance from <hi>Everlaſting Death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Spiritual mercies are the <hi>great mercies.</hi> They are the <hi>Fathers gifts</hi> to his <hi>Children:</hi> other mercies he gives to them that are hated and abhorred by him. They have ſome Relation to God as his Creatures, Servants in his great Family: and therefore they ſhall have ſomewhat here, a portion they ſhall have in theſe common fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, <hi>vile</hi> and <hi>ungodly men</hi> often eſcape deadly dangers as well as <hi>precious Saints,</hi> nay, they may be preſerved, when others better then they are taken a way ſuddenly, and by a violent death. Theſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:136195:18"/>Temporal Benefits will not evidence Gods ſpecial favour in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>What Cauſe have you to whom God hath given thoſe great be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits, of <hi>Juſtification, Adoption, Sanctification,</hi> and hopes of <hi>glory</hi> in <hi>Heaven,</hi> for to ſay with the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> Epheſ. 1.3. <hi>Bleſſed be the God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt who hath bleſſed us with all ſpiritual Bleſſings in Heavenly places in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> And with the Prophet in the Text: <hi>what ſhall</hi> I <hi>Render to the Lord,</hi> who hath done ſo great things for, to deliver my Soul from the <hi>Nethermoſt-Hell,</hi> and to call me to <hi>Eternal glory by Jeſus Christ:</hi> ſay therefore with the Apoſtle <hi>Peter, To him be glory and Dominion for ever and ever,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.10, 11.</p>
               <p>Uſe II. For Humiliation, Hence we have a ground of <hi>humbling and abaſing our ſelves,</hi> in the Conſideration of our great neglect of ſerious obſervation of Gods favours towards us, and alſo of our ſhort returnes we have made to him for them; may not the Lord complain of us as of <hi>Iſrael; Do you thus requite the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.6. It may ſeem unſuitable and unſeaſonable to urge this at ſuch a time, and on ſuch a day, when met to praiſe the Lord for his <hi>great mercies;</hi> But they may well Conſiſt; An heart <hi>ſenſible</hi> of its own <hi>Ingratitude,</hi> and <hi>ſcant Returns</hi> to God, with a bewailing of the ſame, and an heart deſirous to <hi>praiſe him,</hi> and breaking forth in thankful Acknowledgements of his <hi>manifold Benefits,</hi> may ſtand to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. The Confideration of our former unthankfulneſs, and the greatneſs of our Evil therein, and Humiliation for it, may help for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward our Thankfulneſs for preſent and future times.</p>
               <p>Uſe III. By way of <hi>Exhorration.</hi> 1. <hi>To imitate</hi> this holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet of God in <hi>taking notice</hi> of Gods mercies, and in ſpecial of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies to our ſelves; Take notice of all.</p>
               <p>Conſider <hi>the times</hi> when mercies have been given out to you. <hi>All times.</hi> Mercies in your <hi>mothers womb,</hi> mercies in <hi>Childhood,</hi> mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies in <hi>ſingle</hi> and <hi>married Condition;</hi> Common dayes mercies, Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath dayes mercies; view the places where you have received mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; In <hi>Old-England,</hi> on the <hi>Sea;</hi> In this <hi>Country;</hi> In one Town, Family and other, <hi>ſhip mercies</hi> and <hi>Shoar mercies,</hi> mercies at <hi>home,</hi> and mercies <hi>abroad,</hi> mercy at the <hi>Swamp,</hi> mercy in the <hi>houſe or Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Conſider the <hi>kinds of mercy, ſpiritual, temporal, preventing, ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:136195:19"/>ſupplying,</hi> affording ſuccours in a time of great need; as in your <hi>late danger,</hi> healing wounds, reſtoring health and ſtrength, forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and giving further ſpace and time of <hi>Repentance,</hi> thoſe that have been taken away, if they were not prepared for their Change, have no time any more to work in for <hi>Eternity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Conſider the Intereſt in <hi>others mercies</hi> publick or more private; Every one of you may ſay, It was <hi>mercy to me,</hi> that the reſt of the Company were then ſpared beſides my ſelf: If ſeveral others had been cut off beſides thoſe that fell, had not thoſe that eſcaped been much more endangered, what unlikelihood of your preſervation af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward. It is <hi>mercy</hi> that God made you <hi>Inſtrumental</hi> for the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation</hi> of ſo many perſons as were then in that <hi>place, men, women,</hi> and <hi>little ones.</hi> Conſider that it is the <hi>Lords doing</hi> that you are <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned,</hi> and hitherto <hi>preſerved</hi> in your <hi>habitations.</hi> Behold the <hi>work of God,</hi> as in what he did <hi>againſt you,</hi> ſo in what he hath wrought <hi>for you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mot. 1. Conſider it is a <hi>great Evil</hi> not to ponder on, and to Conſider of the <hi>operation of his hands</hi> whether in afflictions, or in mercies, in Salvations, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 28.4, 5.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly.</hi> If we be not obſerving Chriſtians to diſcern and mark all Gods wayes about us, we cannot <hi>ſanctifie Gods Name therein,</hi> as it is our duty to do, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15. All Gods works are a part of his <hi>Name,</hi> he makes himſelf known in his <hi>wiſdome, power, love, goodneſs and mercy</hi> therein. If we ſanctifie not his Name, he will be ſanctified upon us. Therefore, <hi>Behold and ſee,</hi> take notice of all his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3dly.</hi> If we do not <hi>obſerve them our ſelves,</hi> how ſhall we declare them to <hi>others?</hi> This is a duty incumbent on us, <hi>Numb.</hi> 22.31. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.31. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.18. How can we tell to others what <hi>God hath done for us,</hi> if we take not good notice of it <hi>our ſelves?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly.</hi> Be ſtudiouſly ſollicitous <hi>what to Return</hi> to the God of your Salvation; as the Prophet here was, <hi>what ſhall I Render,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="1">I. There is ſomething that God would <hi>not have returned</hi> to him; there is a return that in ſtead of finding acceptance with him is a <hi>provocation</hi> to him. It provokes him to <hi>wrath and Indignation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. God would not have <hi>ſin returned</hi> to him; yet thus did many in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Deut. 32.6. <hi>Iſrael</hi> Gods peculiar people, in Covenant
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:136195:19"/>with him, after great things done for them, did wretchedly and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefully deal with him; they <hi>turned away</hi> from God, and walked after the imagination of their own <hi>evil hearts,</hi> they <hi>forſook the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of living waters,</hi> and <hi>changed their glory,</hi> for that which could not profit. To receive <hi>good</hi> from God and return <hi>ſin</hi> to God is <hi>vile</hi> &amp; <hi>abominable.</hi> It is a very fooliſh thing to give way to ſin againſt God, when we have received mercies, even many and great mercies from him; and therefore it is called <hi>folly:</hi> Pſal 85.8. <hi>that they return not again to folly.</hi> This God complains of in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in <hi>Iſai.</hi> 1.2, 3. I <hi>have brought up Children and they have rebelled against me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beware every one of you here this day that you give not the Lord Cauſe ſo to complain of you; I have <hi>brought up</hi> theſe perſons, I have <hi>bleſſed them</hi> in themſelves, and in their Relations, I have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved them in ſuch <hi>deadly dangers,</hi> I have <hi>rebuked</hi> the <hi>deſtroyer,</hi> I have given them their lives for a <hi>prey,</hi> I have brought them in ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to their <hi>habitations</hi> and <hi>Relations,</hi> I have <hi>healed their wounds,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored them to <hi>health</hi> and <hi>ſtrength,</hi> and Behold they ſtill <hi>rebel</hi> againſt me, they follow their <hi>Luſts,</hi> their <hi>revelling</hi> and <hi>vain Company</hi> ſtill, they ſpend my <hi>Sabbaths looſly</hi> ſtill, they are ſtill <hi>unſavoury</hi> in their <hi>Commnnication;</hi> ſtill <hi>proud, froward:</hi> The Lord takes ſpecial notice how perſons carry it after ſignal mercies, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 26.10.</p>
               <p>In ſpecial take heed of <hi>wantonneſs of Spirit,</hi> and <hi>kicking againſt God</hi> in the enjoyment of his mercies, <hi>kicking</hi> againſt his <hi>word;</hi> againſt <hi>Reproofs,</hi> againſt his <hi>Ordinances</hi> in <hi>Magiſtracy and Miniſtry;</hi> againſt his <hi>Institutions</hi> in his houſe; as too many do in theſe dayes, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.15. <hi>Jeſurun waxed fat and kicked;</hi> Iſrael ſhould have been <hi>Jeſurun.</hi> i. e. righteous or upright before God, but were nothing leſs, when <hi>filled and fatted,</hi> then they <hi>kicked,</hi> like ſome <hi>young,</hi> when they have <hi>ſucked,</hi> kick the <hi>Damms dugs.</hi> Though Parents be liberal to their Children, yet they would not have them <hi>wanton,</hi> and <hi>trample</hi> good meat under their feet, and yet ſuch a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit there is in us; we are ready to turn the very <hi>grace of God</hi> reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Goſpel into <hi>Laſciviouſneſs</hi> as they did, <hi>Jude</hi> 4. and many now do. When Gods mercies make us wanton, this God takes ill; Take heed of <hi>ſniffing</hi> and <hi>trampling</hi> mercies under feet: Be not <hi>wanton, ſecure, proud, ſcornful,</hi> after ſuch a deliverance as this, ſay as <hi>Ezra.</hi> 9.13, 14. ſhall we after ſuch a deliverance again <hi>break thy
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:136195:20"/>Commandments,</hi> &amp;c. Let not <hi>ſin</hi> the only object of <hi>Gods batred</hi> be the <hi>Return</hi> you make to God for his <hi>ſparing, preſerving mercy,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Conſider 1. This will be a great <hi>aggravation</hi> of all your other and former Evils, to ſin after ſuch mercies; as Iſraels <hi>murmurings and Rebellions</hi> in the <hi>wilderneſs</hi> after their <hi>deliverance</hi> at the <hi>red Sea,</hi> and mercies vouchſafed, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 9.10. with 16.17. <hi>verſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. This will bring <hi>worſe and greater Evils,</hi> in one kind or other, <hi>John</hi> 5.14. <hi>ſin no more,</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>leaſt a worſe thing come.</hi> You that eſcaped without the leaſt hurt may come to be dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly wounded; the Bullet may hit you as the Arrow did <hi>Ahab;</hi> you that were then only hurt, when others were ſlain: take heed that God cut you not down ere long for ſuch evil requitals of him for his great goodneſs. Your late <hi>preſervation</hi> may be but a <hi>reſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to ſoarer Judgements.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly.</hi> Return not a <hi>lame and halt Requital;</hi> a body without a Soul, the lip without the Heart, a <hi>verbal</hi> without a <hi>real Sacrifice;</hi> external duties without the Spirit, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.13, 14. <hi>you have brought the torn,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>but curſed be the deceiver who hath a male in his flock,</hi> &amp;c. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.14. <hi>David</hi> and the Princes not only <hi>offer liberally</hi> towards the Temples building; but he bleſſeth God that they ſhould offer ſo <hi>willingly, ſo heartily,</hi> This is that he principally wondereth at, It is a greater mercy from God to give a man a <hi>willing heart</hi> to offer what he doth, then to give him that which he may offer to him.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly.</hi> Affirmatively, <hi>Render to God that which he calls for at our hands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. In general; Render to God <hi>that which is Gods,</hi> Math. 22.21. As that which is <hi>Caeſars muſt be rendred to Caeſar;</hi> ſo that which is <hi>Gods muſt be rendred to God:</hi> give God that which is <hi>his Owne:</hi> give God <hi>his due,</hi> as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 29.1. give to the Lord the <hi>glory due to his Name.</hi> As that which we offer to God muſt be his owne; of his own Appointment and according to his own mind, ſo what is his own ſhould be rendred to him.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly.</hi> More particularly. 1. Render <hi>your ſelves to God:</hi> ſo the Apoſtle exhorts us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1. that we <hi>give up our bodies as a liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and holy, and acceptable Sacrifice,</hi> &amp;c. what ever we are or have, it is from the Lord: you are the Lords by right of <hi>Creation, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> by right of <hi>preſervation,</hi> in the great perils you were
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:136195:20"/>lately in, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Lord hath the moſt right to you. But many will not give God his right; They are and will be their own, <hi>Their Tongues are their own,</hi> as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 12 4. Their <hi>Eſtates their own</hi> to diſpoſe of as they ſee good, as <hi>Nabal,</hi> 1 Sam. 25.11. <hi>My Bread and my Fleſh,</hi> &amp;c. Their time is <hi>their own</hi> to ſpend as they pleaſe, they will not be ruled by God, nor by thoſe whom God ſets over them in <hi>Family, Church or Commen-wealth:</hi> Oh give up your ſelves Souls and bodies to be for God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.19, 20. <hi>glorifie God in your Souls,</hi> &amp;c. Thus did <hi>Paul</hi> Acts 27.23. <hi>whoſe</hi> I <hi>am, and whom I ſerve.</hi> He was Gods, and he gave himſelf to the Service of God in the work he ſet him about. As all that comes from God doth not ſatisfie a gracious heart with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Lord himſelf; no more is the Lord pleaſed with what cometh from us without our ſelves.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly.</hi> Return <hi>love to God,</hi> Pſal. 116.1. I <hi>love the Lord becauſe he hath heard,</hi> &amp;c. This is a good Return. Have not we that have pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to God in any diſtreſſes formerly or lately, or know what prayer means Cauſe to ſay, <hi>The Lord hath heard the voice of our Supplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;</hi> Oh <hi>love the Lord</hi> greatly, intirely with all our hearts. Have you been in great ſtreights, and you have prayed, and God hath ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed you? Have you been in <hi>doubts,</hi> and God hath <hi>reſolved</hi> you? Have you been in <hi>Terrours of Conſcience, affliction of Spirit,</hi> full of <hi>fears</hi> of Gods <hi>Everlasting wrath,</hi> and you ſought God and he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered you, ſcattered your fears, and cauſed the <hi>Sun of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to riſe</hi> and ſhine upon you, and given you <hi>peace?</hi> Have you been in deadly dangers by <hi>ſickneſs,</hi> by <hi>Enemies</hi> that have riſen up againſt you, by <hi>wounds,</hi> and you have prayed for <hi>healing</hi> and delivering mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy? oh then Render Love to God for his goodneſs, mercy, and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
               <p>Mot. 1. Conſider, <hi>gratitude requireth it</hi> at our hands. All our good temporal and ſpiritual is from him; And all is freely beſtowed; yea, his mercies beſtowed on us are more then the <hi>hairs of our Head:</hi> His preventing, ſparing, delivering, ſupplying mercies. He is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore worthy of our Love not only in reſpect of his Excellency in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but alſo of his <hi>benignity and grace</hi> towards us, eſpecially his rich mercy in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly.</hi> Love is the <hi>ground of all duties</hi> acceptably performed to God. All is nothing without Love to God and man, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, 2.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:136195:21"/>All the Commandments are comprized under it, <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.27. It is the <hi>fulſilling of the Law;</hi> Love to God is the fulfilling of the <hi>firſt Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> and love to man the fulfilling of the <hi>ſecond;</hi> where Love abounds there will be much cheerfulneſs, willingneſs and readineſs to do any thing to pleaſe him that is loved.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3dly.</hi> No love ſhall be <hi>loſt that is caſt upon the Lord;</hi> he knows who loves him in <hi>ſincerity,</hi> and he approves them, and will <hi>love them again,</hi> and <hi>manifest his Love</hi> to them, and from his love to them do <hi>wonderful things</hi> for them. <hi>Their labour of Love ſhall not be in vain, Exod</hi> 20.7. <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.9,13. <hi>John.</hi> 14.21, 23. Oh love the Lord who hath redeemed you out of your diſtreſſes, and given you cauſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in his great goodneſs in Anſwer of your prayers; And let your Love to God appear in theſe things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In <hi>hearing the voice of his Commands,</hi> and inclining your Ear to what he calls for from you; This is <hi>Equitable.</hi> If God hear us, let us hear him: ſhall Gods <hi>Ear be open</hi> to our Requeſts, and <hi>our Ears</hi> ſhut to his <hi>Command,</hi> yea, <hi>Intreaties</hi> and <hi>beſeechings,</hi> when he beſeecheth us to give up our ſelves more to him, to follow him and cleave more to him? may not the Lord ſay when we are dull, and ſlow to hear and hearken to his voice; Is this your <hi>love and kindneſs,</hi> do you thus requite me for anſwering your prayers in the day of your trouble?</p>
               <p n="2">2. In <hi>ſhunning all that may ſeparate from God,</hi> and ſeparate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and you; and that for this very cauſe, becauſe they do cauſe a <hi>ſeparation:</hi> And that is <hi>ſin,</hi> Eſai. 59.2. <hi>wants, perſecutions</hi> cannot ſeparate, but it is only <hi>ſin,</hi> The true Love of God is a Love of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> and therefore there muſt be a ſhunning that which cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>ſeparation;</hi> Let us therefore hate all Evil in our ſelves and others, and maniſeſt our hatred in ſeeking the Extirpation and deſtruction of it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 97.10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.9. <hi>Abhorre that which is Evil,</hi> thereby we depart from God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.12. The <hi>Servant</hi> that loved his <hi>maſter</hi> would not depart from him.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Shew your <hi>Love</hi> in <hi>Carefulneſs to pleaſe him in all things;</hi> Children that love their Parents will ſeek to <hi>pleaſe them;</hi> ſo it is with Gods Children, Chriſt loving his Father ſought to pleaſe him in all things, <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.29. Walk as before the face of God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.9. And where there is a Care to pleaſe him, there will be a readineſs to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:136195:21"/>yield <hi>willing obedience</hi> to any Command given even in the moſt diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult duties &amp; Services, <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.10. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.3. unleſs love prevail in the Soul, ſome Command of God or other will be <hi>grievous.</hi> Love makes them eaſy, as to <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 119.97.127. All will ſay they love God, but little Care appears in many men and women to pleaſe God. Some will pleaſe themſelves whither God be pleaſed or no.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Manifeſt your Love to God in your <hi>Love to the Church of God,</hi> Pſal. 122.6.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. In loving <hi>Church Aſſemblies,</hi> Pſal. 42.1, 2. and 26.8. and the <hi>Fellowſhip of all Saints,</hi> Pſal. 16.3.</item>
                  <item>2. In grieving in the <hi>Churches affliction,</hi> and rejoycing in its <hi>proſperity</hi> as <hi>Ietbro, Exod.</hi> 18.9. and <hi>Neh.</hi> 1.4.</item>
                  <item>3. In <hi>ſeeking and promoting</hi> the <hi>Churches welſare</hi> in our mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and according to our power and opportunity, ſo <hi>David</hi> promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 122.7, 8. ſo did <hi>Mordecai,</hi> Eſther 10.3. ſo <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28.</item>
                  <item>4. Manifeſt a ſincere love of God in minding the things of God, whereby he may be honoured, his Name advanced, his Truths pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagated from generation to generation.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Love will ſtick at nothing whereby it may honour God, It is a Bountiful affection. Gods love to man did make him part with his <hi>only begotten Son,</hi> he ſpared not him but gave him to dye, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> John 3.16. <hi>Abraham</hi> will part with his <hi>Iſaack</hi> at Gods Command: nay, Love never knoweth when it hath done enough; It knows no ſuch thing as <hi>too much,</hi> or <hi>too ſoon;</hi> The Soul thinks it cannot be too quick, too forward in any Service of God. It cannot have too much holineſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> nay, when one hath done his beſt, yet he is <hi>aſhamed</hi> he hath done <hi>ſo little;</hi> and though he takes comfort in what he hath been enabled to do, yet he looks at all as <hi>nothing,</hi> as <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 Cor. 12.11. and prayes for ſparing mercy, as <hi>Nehem.</hi> 13.22.</p>
               <p>Thus return love to God: This is a good Return, whereby the Soul takes more Content in God, more delight in Fellowſhip with him, which is the <hi>nature of Love,</hi> Deut. 10.12. That mercy is made an <hi>affliction</hi> to us, that doth not <hi>engage our hearts</hi> to love God more; they ſhould not take off our hearts from the love of God, but quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en us to abound in more love, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 31.23. And therefore you that have been delivered Conſider, It is now ſome time ſince you were
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:136195:22"/>in that diſtreſs, and had ſuch a remarkable deliverance, Is your love to God <hi>Increaſed</hi> by it, Care to pleaſe him, and to walk in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to his holy Commandments, know it, this return God expects from you; and therefore ſee that you ſail not his Expectation.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Return <hi>worſhip to God.</hi> ſo <hi>David</hi> promiſeth to do upon the receipt of mercy from God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.7. In thy <hi>fear will I worſhip,</hi> &amp;c. This we are exhorted to, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.29. <hi>worſhip the Lord in the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of holineſs.</hi> Worſhip him in all his holy Inſtitutions in his houſe. Let ſuch of you as have neglected ſome Ordinances of his worſhip and preparation of your ſelves for them, take heed of neglecting ſtill; God is a Jealous God, he accounts them <hi>haters of him</hi> that do not worſhip him in his own Inſtitutions, when they have liberty and opportunity to enjoy them, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.5. you that are not in <hi>full Church Communion,</hi> either you are <hi>prepared</hi> or <hi>unprepared</hi> with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to your preſent ſtate; If ſtill <hi>unprepared,</hi> yet in a <hi>Carnal ſtate,</hi> what would have become of you, if you had dyed at the Swampe, or in the Garriſon, if you had then been taken away? If you be <hi>prepared</hi> having a <hi>true faith in Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and you neglect his Ordinances God may cut you down by ſome temporal Judgement, though you, be not damned for it: Conſider that place, <hi>Numb</hi> 9.13. The man that is <hi>clean,</hi> and <hi>for beareth to keep the Paſsover, the ſame Soul ſhall be cut off from his people,</hi> becauſe he brought not the offering of the Lord in his appointed ſeaſon, that man ſhall <hi>bear his ſin</hi> As for you that do enjoy all Ordinances in Gods houſe be you exhorted to <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God</hi> in the <hi>participation thereof,</hi> more <hi>ſpiritually</hi> and <hi>chearfully,</hi> ſerve him with more <hi>joy</hi> and <hi>delight,</hi> with more <hi>Reverence</hi> and <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vency</hi> of Spirit.</p>
               <p>In ſpecial, Return <hi>prayer to God;</hi> which is ſuch a principal part of worſhip, that it is ſometimes put for the whole worſhip of God. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.13.</p>
               <p>Be much with God <hi>in prayer:</hi> Thus the prophet here, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116 2. and 13. <hi>verſes,</hi> God having anſwered his prayer and given him ſo great a deliverance, he ſhall therefore <hi>call upon God as long as he lives.</hi> This will be one thing that he will Render to God ſo mercy received, he will be ſtill calling upon God. Let us improve all the Anſwers we have received from God to encourage us to for ther prayer to him.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:136195:22"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Mot.</hi> 1. Conſider, we cannot <hi>weary the Lord with often going to him;</hi> It is ſometimes an Argument of Encouragement in requeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing help or kindneſs from men: He is an old friend, a tryed friend, he hath helped me when I was in a great ſtreight, and therefore I will go to him again: much more here; But, though men may be weary of our often coming to them, yet God will not; he taketh it as a good return, when we are much, yea, more in prayer with him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mot.</hi> 2. When we have <hi>prevailed with God</hi> for any ſpecial mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, deliverance or help in a day of trouble, there is yet great need of <hi>prayer</hi> and <hi>Continuance</hi> thereof.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For a <hi>thankful heart</hi> to the giver of every <hi>good</hi> and <hi>perfect gift;</hi> the <hi>God of our Salvations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. For the <hi>Continuance</hi> of the <hi>mercy,</hi> that it may not be taken away from us; that the Evil removed may not again return.</p>
               <p n="3">3. For the <hi>Sanctification</hi> of the <hi>mercy</hi> and <hi>bleſſing</hi> to us, need to pray for an heart to uſe it in a right manner to the honour of Gods Name and others good.</p>
               <p>That it may not be an <hi>occaſion of ſin</hi> to us, that it may not be <hi>abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi> by us; That when God is good to us, we may not be the worſe in our wayes towards him. There is great need of <hi>prayer to God</hi> in a <hi>time of proſperity,</hi> that we may improve it to glorifie him in our <hi>particular places</hi> wherein we are ſet by him.</p>
               <p n="4">4. we ſhall be yet needing more and <hi>renewed mercies</hi> daily, whilſt we are here in this world, and therefore we muſt be <hi>Beggars</hi> till we get to Heaven: we need more <hi>grace, wiſdome</hi> for our work and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs in our <hi>ſtations;</hi> more <hi>mortification</hi> of our Corruptions, more power againſt our <hi>great Adverſary Satan,</hi> &amp;c. And therefore have we prayed, and obteined what you asked; pray ſtill that you may receive ſtill from the ſame <hi>bountiful hand</hi> gracious Anſwers of your Requeſts. As we are to go to the <hi>Throne rf grace</hi> in our wants; ſo alſo in our Receipts of mercies, that they may be <hi>Continued</hi> and <hi>Sanctified</hi> to us, and alſo improved by us according to his will.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Render <hi>to God the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ows that you have made to him in the time of your Trouble,</hi> in the day of your <hi>great diſtreſs;</hi> pay your <hi>Vows</hi> to the moſt high God; Thus the Prophet in this Pſalm, 14.15. <hi>verſ</hi>-whether your <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ows</hi> have been more <hi>ſolemn,</hi> or only a bare Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your Heart. Have you vowed to forſake any ſin, to leave
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:136195:23"/>any <hi>evil Cuſtome;</hi> to walk more exactly with God, to be more Careful in <hi>Relative duties,</hi> to ſeek more after God in all his wayes, to be more Reverent in attending to Gods worſhip; Oh now be Careful to diſcharge what you have promiſed and reſolved; now pay what you vowed, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 56.12. There ſaith <hi>David, thy <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ows are up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me O God;</hi> the Vows which he had made to God in his danger, lay upon him, as a <hi>Bond</hi> which he muſt look to free himſelf from; he had faſt bound himſelf to God, but he will looſe himſelf by paying them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mot.</hi> 1. It is <hi>folly to Vow and not to pay;</hi> and God <hi>taketh no pleaſure in Fools,</hi> Eccleſ 5.45, 6.</p>
               <p>It is <hi>hateful folly;</hi> Better not have vowed, then vow and not pay.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is a <hi>great Aggravation of ſin,</hi> when it is againſt <hi>ſolemn Vows;</hi> and therefrre take heed to your wayes: If you did not vow in that time of danger, yet you have vowed in your. <hi>Baptiſme;</hi> that you would be the <hi>Lords Servants,</hi> &amp; keep his Commandment; But I doubt not, but that you had ſerious thoughts then on thoſe two or three dayes while your Trouble chieflyl aſted, that if God would return you in <hi>peace</hi> &amp; <hi>Safety</hi> to your Habitations, to the Enjoyment of your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, you would walk more to the praiſe of his Name, and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Goſpel: That if the Lord would preſerve you from <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent</hi> and <hi>ungodly men</hi> that ſought your <hi>Ruine,</hi> you would be more <hi>faithful Servants</hi> to him: Oh take heed to your ſelves, that you forget not the <hi>promiſes</hi> wherein you have bound your Souls: After de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance had from God, <hi>Return not to folly,</hi> Pſal. 85.8.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Conſider, God <hi>hath the Bond,</hi> and it will be called for. Though we may forget and little regard our <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ows</hi> and and the payment of them, yet God remembers all our Vows and <hi>Engagements;</hi> one time or other, we ſhall be put in mind of them. God put <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> in mind of his <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ow,</hi> when he went from his <hi>Fathers houſe,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Gen.</hi> 35.1. &amp;c. God had told him of it once before, <hi>Chap.</hi> 31, 13. It may be, God was diſpleaſed with him for his ſlackneſs to go to <hi>Bethel</hi> and pay it; and therefore though he did not chide him, he being then in heavineſs, yet takes the opportunity, and gently minds him what was his duty, and would be for his ſafety, when ſo full of fears of the Countries riſing againſt him; by Reaſon of that act of his Sons againſt the <hi>Sechemites.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Did you then <hi>Vow,</hi> when in ſo great danger; It was a ſeaſonable
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:136195:23"/>time of vowing; Take alſo the fitteſt ſeaſon for payment. And that is Now, the preſent time, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.14, 18. Now <hi>in the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of his people:</hi> Deferre not.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Return fear to God;</hi> That the Lord expects, that the more he diſcovers his grace and goodneſs, his <hi>mercy</hi> and <hi>Salvation</hi> to us, we ſhould <hi>fear him</hi> the more, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130.4. <hi>There is for giveneſs with thee, that thou maiest be feared;</hi> This is alſo foretold of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> that at their Return out of <hi>Captivity,</hi> they ſhall <hi>fear the Lord and his goodneſs in the latter dayes,</hi> Hoſ. 3. <hi>ult,</hi> The more good you receive from God, the more do you abound in the fear of God; ſo ſhall it be with Gods <hi>ancient people</hi> when the <hi>Redeemer</hi> ſhall come to <hi>Zion,</hi> and ſhall <hi>turn ungodlineſs from Jacob,</hi> the fear of the Lord ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail <hi>mightily</hi> in their <hi>Hearts,</hi> more then ever, The greater Gods goodneſs, the more ſhall the fear of God be upon their hearts. All their joy in God and his goodneſs ſhall be mixed with a <hi>Reverential fear</hi> of God; They ſhall <hi>ſerve the Lord in fear and rejoyes with trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling,</hi> as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.11. ſo let it be with you, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.28. <hi>Serve the Lord with Reverence and godly fear;</hi> fear to offend ſo good a God who hath had ſuch mercy on you, wrought ſuch deliverances for you. And in all your rejoycings and praiſings of God for his goodneſs, ſee that there be a mixture of fear; <hi>work out your Salvation with fear and Trembling,</hi> Phil. 2.12.</p>
               <p>And manifeſt the fear of God in your hearts by your Care to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from all Evil,</hi> Prov. 16.6. And by your uſing the very <hi>Name</hi> and <hi>Attributes</hi> of God with <hi>great Reverence;</hi> by Reverencing Gods Sanctuary, by endeavouring to walk with a <hi>good Conſcience</hi> towards all men: not oppreſſing any, <hi>Levit.</hi> 25.17. not avenging our ſelves though injured, Gen. 42.18. Being <hi>faithful</hi> in all <hi>Trusts</hi> committed to us, <hi>Neh.</hi> 7.2.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Be not high minded, but fear:</hi> not with a <hi>ſlaviſh fear,</hi> to fear him only for his <hi>wrath</hi> and <hi>Judgements,</hi> but alſo for his <hi>Compaſſion</hi> and <hi>goodneſs.</hi> And therefore let our fear of God be joyned with a love of God, to fear him in <hi>Love,</hi> and Love him in fear: Let not our fear drive us from God, as <hi>Cains</hi> did, but cauſe us to cleave cloſet to God, as God promiſeth in <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.40.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Render <hi>true Sanctity</hi> to God. <hi>Be perfecting holineſs in the fear of God,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1. <hi>Math.</hi> 22.21. Render <hi>to God the things that are Gods:</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:136195:24"/>Thus Chriſt ſpake upon their ſhewing him the <hi>penny</hi> that had <hi>Caeſars Image</hi> on it, that man might know that God requireth of man his own <hi>Image</hi> in man himſelf, in which he at firſt Created him, &amp; with which he at firſt <hi>adorned</hi> &amp; <hi>beautified</hi> him, &amp; which was mans <hi>chief Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ey</hi> &amp; <hi>glory Caeſar</hi> would have his Image upon his <hi>Coine:</hi> The Lord would ſee his Image in us: The Image of his <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>holineſs.</hi> Let it be more ſhining: And let it more appear, and be manifeſted in our <hi>doing juſtly, loving mercy, and walking humbly with the Lord our God. Be you holy, for the Lord your God is holy:</hi> yea, <hi>in all manner of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.15 16 <hi>Be you merciful as your Father is merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,</hi> Luk. 6.36. As God is an <hi>univerſal good,</hi> doing good to all, ſo let us every one labour to be a <hi>publick good,</hi> doing good to as many as we have opportunity, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.2, 3. <hi>my goodneſs extends not to thee,</hi> (ſaith <hi>David</hi>) <hi>but to the Saints,</hi> &amp;c. Gal. 6.10 <hi>As we have oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity let us do good to all, eſpcially to thoſe that are of the Houſhold of Faith.</hi> Let us now labour to be like him in <hi>holineſs, goodneſs, Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,</hi> &amp; we ſhall be like him hereafter in <hi>glory</hi> and <hi>Bleſſedneſs.</hi> Let us more &amp; more approve our ſelves the Children of God in reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling him, following of him, walking after him, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.1.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Render to God the fruit that he calls for under his <hi>Huſbandry,</hi> and the wayes he takes with us, that we might be fruitful in well do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. This he calls for and expects from a people for whom he hath done as for us in this wilderneſs: to whom he gives the Goſpel of the Kingdome, who have <hi>Sanctuary Enjoyments,</hi> to whom he vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafeth protection from their Enemies, <hi>Math.</hi> 21.43. The <hi>Kingdom</hi> ſhould be taken from the <hi>unfruitful Iews,</hi> and given to them which ſhould bring forth fruit, render it in the ſeaſon, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 5.2.3, 5, 7. <hi>verſ.</hi> God tells us again and again what he looked for; He looked for <hi>ſweet grapes, good fruits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe fruits are the good works required of us in our Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in duties of <hi>godlineſs Righteouſneſs, Lovs, goodneſs</hi> and <hi>mercy,</hi> which God hath ordeined, <hi>that we ſhould walk in them,</hi> Epheſ. 2.10. This was the <hi>Apoſtles prayer</hi> for the <hi>Philippians,</hi> Chap. 1.11. that they might be <hi>filled with the fruits of Righteouſneſs,</hi> &amp;c. and for the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> Chap. 1.10. that <hi>fruitful in every good work.</hi> The Lord takes great pains with us in his houſe: He is pruning of us by the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fictions he brings upon us, that we might be more fruitful, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.2</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:136195:24"/>
               <p> Bring forth the fruit of Ordinances, and Providences: the fruit of your <hi>dangers, troubles, fears,</hi> and alſo of your <hi>Deliverances</hi> and <hi>Experiences</hi> of Gods help in the time of diſtreſs; Live more to God, leſs to your ſelves, leſs to the world. Labour to abound in the work of God, doing good in all places to all with whom you. Converſe. Do good in your <hi>Communication,</hi> Col. 4.6. by your Example; as the <hi>Theſſolonians</hi> did, 1 <hi>Theſ</hi> 1 7. and the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> 2 Cor 9 2. Their <hi>Zeal</hi> provoked very many. Be fruitful Trees in <hi>Gods Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard,</hi> both in word and deed, doing good to all as you have occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on miniſtred to you, provoking them to <hi>love</hi> and <hi>good works</hi> by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding your forwardneſs in the wayes of Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mot.</hi> 1. Conſider, it is an <hi>honour to the glorious and bleſſed God,</hi> when thoſe that are his people are fruitful; when the Trees that he hath planted are laden with good fruit: when a vine is full of <hi>goodly Cluſters.</hi> It is a Credit to the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ine dreſſer,</hi> when ground yields great Increaſe. It is not only the profit, but the honour of the <hi>Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman,</hi> when <hi>Ewes</hi> bear <hi>Twins,</hi> It is the <hi>Shepards honour;</hi> and ſo when Chriſtians are fruitful; It is the honour and glory of God who is the <hi>Husbandman,</hi> John 15.1. their <hi>Shepard,</hi> Pſal. 23.1. The Lord accounts himſelf honoured, <hi>John.</hi> 15.8. <hi>Herein</hi> is <hi>my Father honoured,</hi> &amp;c. Hereby others are ſtirred up to praiſe God, <hi>Math.</hi> 5.16: 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.12. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.11. They are by Jeſus Chriſt to the praiſe and glory of God. Let this quicken us to <hi>Fruitfulneſs;</hi> For this is the great End of our Lives to bring glory to God, the God of our Life. This ought to be our higheſt End in all, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.31.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Fruitful Chriſtians are the Lords delight:</hi> They are <hi>Hephzi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bab,</hi> his delight is in them; <hi>They walk worthy of the Lord to all well pleaſing,</hi> Col. 1.10. The Lord promiſeth to be as the <hi>Dew</hi> unto <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael;</hi> and then his beauty ſhould be as the <hi>Olive Tree,</hi> and his <hi>ſmell</hi> as <hi>Lebanon,</hi> Hoſ. 14.5, 6. The beauty of the <hi>Olive Tree is to be full</hi> of <hi>Olives;</hi> ſuch Chriſtians are beautiful in Gods Eyes; <hi>Lebanon</hi> was full of <hi>ſweet Trees</hi> and <hi>fragrant Flowers,</hi> and filled all the parts thereabouts with a <hi>ſweet ſmel;</hi> and ſo ſhould <hi>Iſrael</hi> be a <hi>ſweet ſavour</hi> to God; when they brought forth good fruit to him. The <hi>Philip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pians fruitfulneſs</hi> in well doing communicating to <hi>Paul</hi> was an odour of a <hi>ſweet ſmell,</hi> a <hi>Sacrifice acceptable and well pleaſing to God,</hi> Phil. 4.18.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:136195:25"/> 3. <hi>Fruitleſs Profeſſors are near unto a Curſe,</hi> and in danger of being plucked up or cut down, <hi>Math,</hi> 21 19. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.8. If we bring not forth fruits of <hi>mercies, deliverances, Ordinances, Afflictions,</hi> if bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren under all, the <hi>Curſe</hi> may come, and God ſay <hi>never fruit grow on you more;</hi> yea, God may cut us down by the <hi>Axe</hi> of his Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which he hath brought upon us, <hi>Math.</hi> 3.10. Now God is lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Axe,</hi> if not <hi>to the Root,</hi> yet he <hi>is lopping</hi> off many branches: and therefore the more need to take heed of <hi>unfruitfulneſs.</hi> The <hi>Jews</hi> were a <hi>fruitleſs Vine</hi> Chriſt layed the <hi>Axe to the Root of the Tree,</hi> &amp;c. Luk. 13.7. <hi>Cut it down,</hi> &amp;c. would we not be cut down and caſt into the Fire, let us be fruitful and that in due <hi>ſeaſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. The End of <hi>Fruitfulneſs in Gods wayes is Everlaſting Life and Bleſſedneſs,</hi> Rom. 6, 32. The good we do in <hi>Family, Town, Church,</hi> being done in uprightneſs will turn to good Account in the great day of Chriſts appearance, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.17. All good fruit which we here bring forth is as <hi>Seed ſown,</hi> 2 Cor. 9.6. Prov. 11.30. It will yield <hi>great increaſe,</hi> 1 Tim. 6.18, 19. 2 Tim. 1.16, 17, 18. you would willingly have the Reward, then do the work; If you would have a <hi>good Crop</hi> in the <hi>Harveſt day,</hi> now be <hi>ſowing</hi> and that not <hi>ſparingly;</hi> ſerve the Lord <hi>faithfully</hi> and <hi>diligently</hi> in duties of <hi>holineſs, Righte. ouſneſs, Love, kindneſs, Bounty and all goodneſs,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.8. know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>your labour is not in vain in the Lord.</hi> Labour to be more and more fruitful, that your works may be more at the laft, then at the firſt; as Chriſt ſpeaks of them, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.19. yea, be fruitful in Age, honouring God, and <hi>adorning the Goſpel in all things,</hi> Pſal. 92.14.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Make this <hi>Return to God for all his Benefits,</hi> and the great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverances received, to make him your Truſt and Confidence all your dayes. Truſt upon the Lord, &amp; live in dependance upon him for further mercy and Salvation. In Experience of what you have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from God, reſt upon him, we need daily from God, and the Lord gives out daily unto us, let us act Faith daily upon God. Make this uſe of Gods gracious appearance for you, never to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt him what ever your <hi>dangers</hi> and <hi>ſtreights,</hi> or <hi>diſtreſſes</hi> may be, ſo it was with <hi>holy Paul,</hi> 2 Cor. 1.10. who delivered us from ſo great a death, and doth deliver, in whom we truſt that he will yet deliver us. Be not overmuch Careful or fearful in theſe evil and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſomedayes. Be not ſollicitous <hi>what you ſhall eat, or what you
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:136195:25"/>ſhall drink, or whire with you ſhall be clothed,</hi> or how you ſhall be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved; <hi>Truſt on the Lord Jehovah in whom is Everlaſting ſtrength,</hi> Iſai. 26.4. the Lord provided for his people daily in the wilderneſs, though they had no bread left in the Evening: yet they had it near their doors in in the morning: he was a ſhadow in the day time from the heat, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Iſai. 4.5, 6. This was <hi>Davids Reſolution</hi> having had ſuch <hi>wonderful deliverances</hi> from all his Enemies, he would ſtill truſt in God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.2. And therefore in his greateſt fears there ſhall be his Conſidence, that he will not <hi>fear what man can do to him,</hi> Pſal. 56.3, 4. He is, and will be a <hi>Buckler to all thoſe that truſt in him,</hi> Pſal. 18.30. It is a very ill Requital not to truſt him by reſting on his promiſes: not to rely upon his <hi>wiſdome, power, faithfulneſs</hi> when we have had much Experience of his <hi>Care, Love, Compaſſion</hi> and <hi>won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful works</hi> for our good. It is <hi>high Ingratitude.</hi> Hence the Lord was ſo angry with <hi>Aſa</hi> for ſending to <hi>Benhadad</hi> for his help, (though there were other evils in it) that he relyed not on God, when God had given him ſuch a <hi>glorious victory</hi> over that <hi>mighty Hoſt</hi> of the <hi>Ethiopians,</hi> 2 Chron. 16: 8, 9: Thereby he provoked God from that time to afflict him with Warrs. Learn to truſt in God in the moſt <hi>deadly dangers:</hi> Let him be your Refuge in all Storms: He is able to keep that which is committed to him. To him <hi>belong the Iſſues from death,</hi> Pſal 68.26:</p>
               <p n="9">9. Make this <hi>Return to God</hi> for all his Bounty and mercy to you, to make God your exceeding joy, as <hi>David</hi> did, Pſal: 43: 4: and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice in him the <hi>God of your Salvation:</hi> yea, the God of all <hi>Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions Temporal, Spiritual, and Eternal:</hi> You cannot praiſe the Lord aright, nor walk worthy of him, except you rejoyce in him, <hi>Pſal,</hi> 33.1. <hi>Rejoyce in the Lord you Righteous, for praiſe is comely for the upright.</hi> This duty is urged upon the Saints, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.1. and 4.4. <hi>Rejoyce in the Lord alwayes, and again I ſay Rejoyce.</hi> We ſhould not only rejoyce before the Lord in his bleſſings that he vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feth us; as <hi>Life, health, Corn,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.12.18. That God alloweth, yea, enjoyneth his people, but, <hi>Rejoyce in the Lord;</hi> Let not our joy be <hi>Carnal</hi> in our preſervation from death, in the Lifes of our Relations, in Crops, houſes, Lands, Children; but let our joy be <hi>Spiritual.</hi> Let not our chief joy be in <hi>Church Priviledges,</hi> and <hi>Ordinances;</hi> but on Chriſt Jeſus. Such are the <hi>true Circumciſion,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:136195:26"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:136195:26"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:136195:27"/>who rejoyce in Chriſt Joſus, and put no Confidence in the Fleſh,</hi> Phil. 3.3. Pſal. 97 12. Rejoyce not in ſin, that is an ill Requital; <hi>the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of ſin are but for a Seaſon,</hi> and that joy will End in ſorrow: but <hi>Rejoyce in the Lord,</hi> and that <hi>joy can no man take from you.</hi> And that we may the more rejoyce in him; Let us endeavour to be more clearing up our Intereſt in him, as our God in Chriſt Jeſus. That we may be able to ſay, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 48.14. This <hi>God of Salvation is our God;</hi> well may they rejoyce in God that have him for their God, for then he will be their guide unto death, their God for ever &amp; ever.</p>
               <p n="10">10. and Laſtly: Render to God <hi>praiſe and Thanksgiving,</hi> ſo the Prophet promiſeth in verſe after the Text; <hi>I will take the Cup of Salvation;</hi> wherein he alludes to their ſolemn feaſts, wherein they had <hi>Cups,</hi> and in the uſe of them they returned praiſe to God for the bleſſing they had received from him. Commemorate Gods mercies to our ſelves and others, and praiſe his <hi>great,</hi> his <hi>holy,</hi> and <hi>Reverend Name,</hi> this we are frequently exhorted to, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.25. And 61.8 And 107:13, 14, 15: you were as priſoners ſhut up for a time, but God hath brought you out into a large place: <hi>Oh give Thanks to the Lord for he is good, for his mercy endureth for Ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moi:</hi> 1. God hath given you your deſires, and Anſwered your prayers, therefore do you Anſwer his Expectation, what Cauſe have you to bleſs the Name of the Lord, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66:19, 20: ſo <hi>David,</hi> veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God hath heard me, he hath been Attentive to the voice of my prayer: Bleſſed be God which hath not turned away my prayer nor his mercy from me, as <hi>Hannah</hi> ſaid to <hi>Eli,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1:27. For this Child I prayed, <hi>&amp;c:</hi> ſo may we ſay, for this mercy I prayed for this deliverance, for this Return to our Habitations, and Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for this dayes liberty we ſought the Lord, and he hath given us, our hearts deſire; he might have made more breaches, continued our diſtreſſes longer, let therefore the Redeemed of the Lord ſay; <hi>The Lord is good and gracious for his mercy endures for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. This is the way to keep and hold Gods bleſſings ſtill with us. It is <hi>via Conſervandi;</hi> God will not take away his mercies from us, from the Country, if we Return praiſe to him; They giving God his <hi>Rent,</hi> the <hi>Tribute</hi> he expects, he will not turn them out of <hi>doors,</hi> not ſtrip us of his Benefits, By <hi>giving praiſe we glorifie him, Pſal.</hi> 50.23. <hi>He that offereth</hi> or ſacrificeth <hi>praiſe glorifies me.</hi> He acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:136195:27"/>his <hi>glorious Attributes,</hi> as in going to God by Petition, ſo in the Sacrifice of praiſe and gratulation.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>In praiſing him we give him the glory of his goodneſs</hi> in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of good to us, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.68. <hi>Thou art good and doſt good,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Bonum eſt ſui diffuſivum:</hi> It is the nature of goodneſs to be <hi>Communicative.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>The glory of his mercy,</hi> in pittying us in our miſcry, doing ſo much for us, who had plunged our ſelves into a <hi>Sea of miſery.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing our own <hi>Indignity,</hi> we acknowledge all to be from <hi>mercy,</hi> Lam. 3.22. as the Church then, ſo may we ſay now; <hi>It is the Lords mercy we are not conſumed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>The glory of his wiſdome,</hi> in ordering all <hi>Events</hi> for his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples good, and ruling all the world for his <hi>Churches benefit: All is theirs,</hi> 1 Cor. 3.21, 22.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>The glory of his power,</hi> in Effecting all thoſe things for us, which we our ſelves could not do, we cannot help our ſelves with any mercy; not make the Sun to riſe, a drop of Rain to fall, nor Cauſe the Earth to bring forth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> All is the work of God, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.11, 12. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 26.12.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>The glory of his Truth in his Word;</hi> making good the ſame to us, and to his Church, <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.3. ſo in that Song after their Victory over the Beaſt; <hi>Juſt and true are thy wayes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mot.</hi> 3. This will open <hi>Gods heart</hi> and <hi>hand</hi> to give more; and ſo it is <hi>medium impretandi,</hi> a means to prevail for more mercies, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.22. And when they began to ſing and to praiſe, the Lord ſet <hi>Ambuſhments</hi> againſt the Children of <hi>Ammon,</hi> &amp;c. a man puts in but a <hi>Bucket</hi> full of water into a <hi>Pump,</hi> but it return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth more: The more praiſe we return, the more good ſhall we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive. A thankful Chriſtian is a bleſſed Chriſtian; would you have future mercies be thankful for preſent mercies, ſay not: If I had ſuch a mercy I could be thankful, and praiſe the Name of the Lord; praiſe him for what thou haſt received, and thou maieſt have more; God will ſhowr down his bleſſings of grace and goodneſs upon thee</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4thly.</hi> Theſe praiſes of God rightly performed are very <hi>accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table</hi> to God; They are <hi>delitiae Caeli,</hi> God delights in them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.15. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.30, 31. And that ſhould make us more delight in this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, becauſe it is ſo pleaſing to God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.3. <hi>He Inhabits the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:136195:28"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:136195:28"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:136195:29"/>praiſes of Iſrael;</hi> He loves to ſit by them, and to hear them when their hearts are in <hi>Tune,</hi> when they ſound forth his <hi>high praiſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5thly.</hi> It is a ſigne that the good things which we enjoy are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as bleſſings from the hand of a <hi>Fathers love,</hi> when they work this in us, to carry up our Affections to be much in bleſſing him for them; A man may abound in good things which are in themſelves bleſſings, and yet be no bleſſing to him that hath them; but be turned into Curſes: How may I know (will ſome ſay) that this and that gift, theſe deliverances are bleſſings to us? even hereby, when they work this diſpoſition in us to bleſs and praiſe the Lord who hath ſo bleſſed us.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>6thly. It is a moſt Heavenly duty,</hi> the very work of the Saints in Heaven; When all other work Ceaſeth, this ſhall not Ceaſe to all Eternity. The more you are in the Exerciſe of this <hi>Spiritual Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,</hi> the more there is of the <hi>Life of Heaven upon Earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This day you meet together to praiſe the Name of the Lord, who were together in ſuch a danger, that you almoſt deſpaired of Life; as the Apoſtle ſaith, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.8. Look that your praiſes be ſuch that God may be well pleaſed with them; and with you in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of this Service.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Let them be Cordial,</hi> with the heart, yea, with the whole heart, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.1.</p>
               <p n="1">1. See that your hearts be taken up with an <hi>Admiration</hi> of <hi>Gods favour</hi> and <hi>Bounty</hi> towards you, as <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 139.14. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire the Lords <hi>ſparing, delivering,</hi> and <hi>reſtoring mercy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. All our Service and worſhip of God muſt be with the heart and from the heart; God calls for the Heart in all, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.26. He would have the Heart in prayer, praiſe, hearing the word, and all other performances; the Lord <hi>is n Spirit, and will be worſhipped in Spirit and Truth,</hi> John 4.24.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Let them be Verbal, Pſal.</hi> 34.1. and 51.15. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.2. <hi>We will Render the Calves of our lips.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. In ſinging <hi>Pſalms,</hi> a duty in <hi>Goſpel times:</hi> Col 3.16. And then moſt <hi>ſeaſonable</hi> when God gives Cauſe of Rejoycing in his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, <hi>James</hi> 5.13. <hi>If any be merry let him ſing Pſalms,</hi> Pſal. 126.1, 2. when the Lord turned the <hi>Captivity</hi> of <hi>Zion,</hi> &amp;c. our mouth was filled with <hi>Laughter</hi> and our <hi>Tongues</hi> with <hi>ſinging.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:136195:29"/> 2. In declaring <hi>Gods goodneſs</hi> unto others; Extolling his Name, ſpeaking of his loving kindneſs, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.18. <hi>Come hither</hi> (ſaith the Prophet) <hi>all you that fear God, and I will tell what he hath done for my Soul.</hi> What Deliverances I have received, and Victories I have obtained, what Anſwers of prayer I have had. So <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.21. <hi>my mouth ſhall ſpeak the praiſe of the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. In <hi>Luk.</hi> 8.38, 39. Chriſt Commands the man out of whom he had caſt the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils to ſhew how great things God hath done for him.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Let them be real praiſes;</hi> praiſe him not only in our words, but in all our wayes; living to the honour of his Name, which is called upon us, and of the Goſpel profeſſed by us, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.27. Only <hi>let your Converſation be at becomes the Goſpel of Chriſt;</hi> That is a main thing to be attended to, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.23. He that will offer praiſe aright, muſt alſo order his Converſation aright; Confeſſion and Converſation muſt go together in a thankful man, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.8, 9. <hi>I will walk before God in the Land of the living;</hi> Inward Affection muſt be manifeſted in our outward Converſation. Therefore look well to your wayes, Elder and younger; walk holily and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly; <hi>live ſoberly, Righteouſly and godly in this preſent world,</hi> elſe all your praiſes are vain; The Lord will not accept them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let our praiſes be Continual,</hi> Pſal. 34.1. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63.4. <hi>I will bleſs thee while I live;</hi> Reſt not in the work of a day, but remember Gods mercies all your dayes; Be not like the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> Pſal. 106.12. They ſang his praiſes, but ſoon forgot his works.</p>
               <p>You that are young remember the Lord in your beſt dayes, and let us all both Elder and younger remember him all our dayes. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member him, to Love him, ſerve, honour and glorifie him. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber your Promiſes and Engagements to him. If we remember not his mercies to praiſe him, he will remember our Ingratitude againſt him therein, by Cutting us ſhort of his bleſſings, and plaguing us with his Judgements.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Let all our Sacrifices of praiſe be offered up to God in the Name of Jeſus Chriſt, that ſo they may be a ſweet ſavour before him. God ſmelled a ſweet ſavour in <hi>Noahs Sacrifice,</hi> after that <hi>wonderful preſervation</hi> from the Floud of waters, Gen. 8.20. <hi>Noah</hi> looked to Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.15. Col. 3.17. In him God will be well pleaſed with you. And that Teſtimony you ſhall have one day from him,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:136195:30"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:136195:30"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:136195:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>that you pleaſed him in your returns to him: Let us thus now Render to God whiles we are here on Earth, and we ſhall Reap the Fruit of all in the great day of Chriſts appearance, when God will <hi>Render to every one according to their works,</hi> Rom. 2.6, 7. Then thoſe that have carefully obſerved all Gods diſpenſations about them, and been follicitous what to Render to him; giving up themſelves to him. Loving, fearing, and obeying him, walking in <hi>holy Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> with him in his own Appointments, they ſhall be received by him into his <hi>Everlaſting Kingdome,</hi> there to be with him, <hi>ſinging praiſes to him that ſits on the Throne, and to the Lamb for Evermore.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:136195:31"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:136195:32"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:136195:32"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
